<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the episcopacy, liturgies, and ecclesiastical ceremonies of the primitive times and of the mutations which happened to them in the succeeding ages gathered out of the works of the ancient fathers and doctors of the church / by John Lloyd, B.D., presbyter of the church of North-Mimmes in Hertfordshire.</title>
            <author>Lloyd, John, Presbyter of the Church of North-Mimmes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2655A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21763</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12739209</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12739209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books,1641-1700 ; 987:17 or 1705:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the episcopacy, liturgies, and ecclesiastical ceremonies of the primitive times and of the mutations which happened to them in the succeeding ages gathered out of the works of the ancient fathers and doctors of the church / by John Lloyd, B.D., presbyter of the church of North-Mimmes in Hertfordshire.</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, John, Presbyter of the Church of North-Mimmes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.G. for John Sherley ... and Robert Littlebury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. LX. [1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 987:17 as Wing L2659 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) and at reel 1705:11 as Wing L2655A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York and Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopacy.</term>
               <term>Church history --  Primitive and early church, ca. 30-600.</term>
               <term>Fathers of the church.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE EPISCOPACY, LITURGIES, AND ECCLESIASTICAL CEREMONIES OF THE PRIMITIVE TIMES, AND Of the mutations which happened to them in the fucceeding Ages: GATHERED Out of the Works of the ancient Fathers and Doctors of the Church.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Lloyd</hi> B. D. Presbyter of the Church of <hi>North-Mimmes</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Let your moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Multum ſacerdotalis officii meritum ſplendeſcit, ubi ſic ſummorum ſervatur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritas, ut in nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inferiorum putatur imminuta libertas.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Leonis Epiſt. 61.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Epiſcopi ſacerdotes ſe eſſe noverint, non Dominos; honorent clericos quafi clericos, ut &amp; ipſis à clericis, quaſi Epiſcopis honor deferatur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hierom.</hi> ad <hi>Nepotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> De vita clericorum.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> for <hi>John Sherley</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Pelican,</hi> and <hi>Robert Littlebury</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Unicorn</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> M.DC.LX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Reverend Father in God IOHN LORD BISHOP OF EXCESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the dark night of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions was by Gods wonderful mercy, (never to be forgotten) well nigh at an end, by the near approaching of our Sun, the breath of our noſtrils, our dread Soveraign Lord the Kings Majeſty, unto the horizon of his paenitent and loyal Subjects in his hereditary Kingdomes and Dominions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:93080:3"/>all began to be revived, &amp; to be prepared for the receiving all good impreſſions: in this beginning of our happineſs, (conſidering with my ſelf by what beſt means men of different apprehenſions concerning Eccleſiaſtical things might be brought unto godly unity and meet uniformity therein;) I thought that the knowledge of the ſtate of the Church of Chriſt in the Apoſtles dayes, and in the four Centuries following their times, (as to the form of Eccleſiaſtical Government, Diſcipline, Liturgy and Rites, uſed in them) would very much conduce to the attainment of that bleſſed end. For in thoſe dayes many thouſands of holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Martyrs flouriſhed; in thoſe times lived the moſt reverend Fathers of the firſt four general Councils, of <hi>Nice, Conſtantinople, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> celebrated over all the Chriſtian world; of whoſe wiſdome and godly care, to do nothing in thoſe particulars againſt the inſtitutions of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, but rather to do all things as might be moſt pleaſing to God, and moſt conducing to the edification of the Church, no prudent and charitable man can enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the leaſt doubt: Men they were, and might erre; but that ſo many men of extraordinary ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and wiſdome, compared to the beſt men of theſe latter Centuries, ſhould unanimouſly agree
<pb facs="tcp:93080:3"/>for the ſpace of two, three or four hundred years in ſetting up and practiſing ſuperſtition, is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible to them who believe that God hath promiſed to teach the humble his way, and ſhew his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to them that fear him, and not to forſake them which have not firſt forſaken him. Having therefore reaſon and religion to aſſure me, that all underſtanding and ſober men, if they could once ſee the form of Church-government, with the Liturgies and Rites uſed by thoſe Primitive Churches, demonſtrated by undeniable teſtimonies of pure antiquity, would eaſily be induced to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them ſo far as they ſhould appear to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for Chriſtian unity and edification, in the preſent circumſtances of time, place, and perſons, (whereof not private men, but the Governours Civil and Eccleſiaſtical are the onely Judges on earth) I made what inquiry I could, if any book were extant in the Engliſh tongue containing a brief, full, and plain demonſtration of all the ſaid Eccleſiaſtical things, which might be had at a cheap rate, ſoon read over, and eaſily underſtood by all men of indifferent capacity, whereby the knowledge of thoſe things might be the more divulged: But, after diligent inquiry, finding none, I reſolved (being the work was within the limits of my vocation, and in reading
<pb facs="tcp:93080:4"/>the ancient writers, I had with no ſmall diligence noted the paſſages conducing thereto) <hi>invocato Dei Opt. Max. Nomine,</hi> to uſe my poor talent with my beſt indevour to write ſuch a little book, which ſhould comprehend in it the ſum and ſubſtance of all the matters above ſpecified, as briefly, fully and plainly as I could. And this was the beginning of this ſmall Treatiſe; which, being ended in convenient time, was offered to worthy men of excellent indowments to be peruſed by them, in hope that one or other of them (knowing the uſefulneſs of the matter treated of, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the too plain, low, and uneven manner of writing) would be moved to put forth a work upon that ſubject; which (being repleniſhed with good variety of well ordered matters, adorned with convenient eloquence, and commended by the worthy name of an Author famous for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, eloquence, and vertues) would be by all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily entertained, greedily read, and would ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convey the things deſired to be publiſhed, to the knowledge of all men. But herein my hope failed me: For thoſe worthy perſons were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the high and weighty affaires of the Church, that they had no leiſure to go about this, (although an uſeful work, yet) of leſs profit to the Church and leſs proportionable to their great abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:93080:4"/>then the ſublime imployment, wherein their time was ſpent. What remained then, but that either that needful work muſt be altogether want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or this poor treatiſe ſo void of due ornaments muſt be ſuffred to go abroad. I had indeed once in a manner reſolved to bury it in my ſtudy, but an occaſion bringing the matterr into a new debate, I ſuffered ſome reaſons to prevaile with me to give it leave to preſent it ſelf to the view of the world; yet not without ſome honourable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron the glorious luſtre of whoſe great learning, Excellent Vertues and pretious name might both illumminate it, and conciliate for the mean and obſcure author ſome room in the good esteem and affection of learned and good men. For which end I thought it moſt convenient to make choiſe of one of thoſe very bright ſtars, which his Majeſties wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodneſs had been pleaſed to ſet in the firmament of our Church: among whom your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was firſt preſented to my thoughts in your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry learned, elegant and eloquent works, eſpecially both in your teſtification of your great and very remarkable zeal for the now moſt bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saint and Martyr our late glorious King <hi>CHARLS</hi> the firſt, and in your no leſs zealous fidelity to our moſt dear and dread Soveraign Lord King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the ſecond, manifeſted in
<pb facs="tcp:93080:5"/>times of greateſt peril, and alſo in your ſighs, groans, complaints and prayers for and of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her deep diſtreſs, in your prudent &amp; indefatigable endevours for her reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in thoſe parts of your Lordſhips moſt learned writings, wherein, as in exceeding fair monuments more laſting then braſſe, you conſecrate the bleſſed Memories of many very precious names, <hi>viz.</hi> of the right reverend Fathers, Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Potter,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Brownrigg,</hi> and other honourable perſons, never to be remembred without due acknowledgement of their tranſcendent worth: and eſpecially, of the moſt reverend Father in God, Dr. <hi>James Uſher</hi> late Arch-biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and Lord Primate of all <hi>Ireland;</hi> who, in an exact knowledge of all good learning, in depth of judgment, in the due ſtating and well cleering controverſies of Religion, and in ſanctity of life, was not much (if at all) inferior to any the beſt of Biſhops ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes; And laſty, in an acceptable taſt which I have had of the ſweetneſs of your vertue in a particular favour, for which I preſent my humble thanks to your Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe you, right reverend father, to take this ſmall work into your honorable patronage and protection, and, pardoning my boldneſs in this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
<pb facs="tcp:93080:5"/>to take in good part the very humble and hearty tender of my beſt ſervice to your Lordſhip. God Almighty long continue your life and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Eſtate, and make you a happy instrument of much good to his Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips in all Duty</hi> John Lloyd <hi>Praesb.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THis ſhort treatiſe containeth the ſum and ſubſtance of what the reverend Doctors of the Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for the firſt four hundred years after the birth of our bleſſed Saviour have practiſed and written, and thereby tranſmitted to our times, concerning Epiſcopacy, Presbytery, Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, Liturgy and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, omitting onely thoſe which appear to be impertinent to the ſtate and condition of the preſent times. Every mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial point herein is proved out of authors received by all ſides (which cauſed the omiſsion of the teſtimony of <hi>Ignatius, &amp;c.</hi>) and ſuch authors againſt whom it cannot be reaſonably preſumed, that they were deceived or erred in their relation of matters of fact and practiſe, done or uſed in the times, wherein they themſelves or thoſe with whom they converſed, did live. The authorities were not collected by the help of tables, or received from ſecond hands (whence miſtakes do eaſily and uſually ariſe) but were taken from the authors own work read and duely conſidered. Becauſe the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by reaſon of humane infirmities in all, and perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in many, is in many parts thereof-diverſely underſtood, it is very needful (ſaith <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi>) that the line of Prophetical and Apoſtolical interpretation be directed according to the rule of Eccleſiaſtical and Catholick ſenſe. And alſo in the very Catholick Church great care muſt be had,<note place="margin">Adverſus hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. c. 2.</note> (ſaith the ſame ancient author) that we hold that
<pb facs="tcp:93080:7"/>which hath been believed every where, alwayes, and by all. Which direction of this diſcreet Writer,<note place="margin">In ipſa item Catholica Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia magno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre curandum eſt, ut id tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus quod ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, quod ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, quod ab omnibus credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> rightly underſtood and applied, is very good, and is and hath been of ſingular uſe, eſpecially againſt Schiſmaticks and Hereticks. For when the conſent of the Catholick Church in her principal members in all the parts of the world, and in all ages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in, and proceeding from the Apoſtolicall times, unto any other ſet or propoſed age, doth clearly appear to be in any Divine Doctrine, Diſcipline, Liturgie, Rites, or any Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall uſage, who can gainſay that unanimous judgment of all the Saints of God, which is a far better interpreter of the word of God, then any generall councell can be? who dare refuſe to embrace the ſentence of that juſt and impartiall Iudge, except in decrees about things in their nature and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally mutable, which may by the good leave of that Judge be with honour layed aſide, when they become unprofitable or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous to the edification and peace of the Church? The Eccleſiaſticall inſtitutions which want ſufficient evidence to prove their approbation by the Church flouriſhing in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes, and are found to have the generall approbation of the Churches between the times of the Apoſtles, and about the year of our Lord <hi>500,</hi> although they be of leſs eſteem and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard then the inſtitutions known to be received by the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Church, yet are they Venerable and worthy of very great regard: partly, becauſe of the propinquity of thoſe Churches, to the time of the Apoſtles, from whom ſome of them might be probably thought to be derived, although a certaine proofe of their derivation appeared not to ſucceeding ages: partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the eminent wiſdome of the Fathers, and exemplary ſanctity of the Churches in thoſe times, in compariſon of the Churches in the following Generations. The Churches of this ſpace of time; that is, between the Apoſtles deceaſe and the
<pb facs="tcp:93080:7"/>year <hi>500.</hi> wanted the extraordinary Apoſtolicall Spirit, which ſo guided the Church, planted by them in all publick reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſhe would make no Ordinance without the Apoſtles approbation, and having it, ſhe could not erre in her deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations. All other Churches therefore might eaſily erre, and they that upon good occaſion given them would modeſty affirm, that they did erre in ſome conſtitutions and uſages generally approved by them, and alſo in ſome remote concluſions of the Divine Doctrine, are not to be thought to diſparage them, ſeeing upon the matter they ſay no more, then that they were men which wanted the guide of the holy Spirit to lead them infallibly to truth and goodneſs in all things of Eccleſiaſticall concernment; but that thoſe Churches within the firſt <hi>500</hi> years erred in any publick conſtitutions or cuſtomes unto Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, or, which is leſs, unto apparent ſuperſtition, is a thing improbable and incredible to them, who rightly conſider the publick doctrine and Eccleſiaſticall Ordinances of thoſe times, and take due notice of the great prudence and holineſs of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the chief Governors and Pillars of thoſe Churches; Hereticks, Idolaters and ſuperſtitious perſons were in many of the Churches, but that the Churches themſelves in any part of that time became Haereticall, Idolatrous, or Superſtitious, is very untrue and unworthy the thought of a prudent and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable man. And here by the way, concerning the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if we compare her in her legall conſtitution with any other Church after the year of our Lord <hi>180.</hi> it will be found that they who charge her with Antichriſtianiſme, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, or Superſtition in her conſtitution, eſtabliſhed by Law, do by clear conſequence paſs the ſentence of the ſame condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon every of thoſe Churches, eſpecially them of the 4th and 5th century: the raſhneſs and injuſtice of which cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is very worthy of a very ſevere cenſure. The Apoſtle, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb facs="tcp:93080:8"/>ſaith that the myſtery of iniquity began to work in his time:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.24.</note> but did he meane thereby that the myſterious iniquity and depth of Satan, began to work in the publick conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Catholick Church in his dayes, and that they were parts of the conſtitutions? no ſurely, neither can any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an be ſo ſimple or ſo injurious to the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles, and the purity of that Church, as to think that the Apoſtle had any ſuch meaning. The myſtery of Iniquity was indeed in the Church in ſome dead branches, in ſome wicked livers and Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, but it was not of the Church, it was no part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Church, although it did labour to inſinuate and work it ſelf into it: it may be granted as very probable, that the myſtery of iniquity in particular, and thoſe dead members, and by them working upon the Churches, might more vitiate the Churches of the ſecond century then the Churches in the firſt century, and the Churches in the third century, more then the Churches of the ſecond and ſo of the reſt to the end of the fifth century; but that in any part of that time it prevailed ſo far, as to become a part of the Eccleſiaſticall Doctrine, Diſcipline, Liturgy or Ceremonies univerſally received and uſed, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſurmiſe of an exceſs of jealouſy, then an opinion ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon probable reaſons, it is ſo far from being an approved truth. After the year <hi>500.</hi> and the diviſion of the Empire, and eſtabliſhment of the Kings,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12, 13.16.</note> which were to give their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and ſtrength to the Beaſt, and which in due time were to burn the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Churches grew generally more and more corrupt; the civill and Eccleſiaſticall confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions attending the Warrs in the ſeverall Provinces, giving advantage to the myſtery of Iniquity, to mingle it ſelf, firſt with the Diſcipline and Ceremonies, and after with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine; whereby, firſt ſuperſtition, then Idolatry, and laſtly, Hereſies took place in the publick profeſſion of the
<pb facs="tcp:93080:8"/>Churches; ſo that in perſons who knowingly ſwallowed the good and bad together, the infection of the myſtery of Iniquity hindred the operation of the good portion of the whole lump, and working the effect of its poyſon into their vital parts, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and deſtroyed them. And therefore theſe latter Churches were not by the firſt reformers of our Church propoſed, for patterns, as the former were, which preſerved the purity of Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Ceremonies without the addition of any thing cauſing Superſtition, much leſs Idolatry or Haereſy. Our Church hath ſeparated the Pretious from the Vile, the good of Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Rites from the peſtiferous and noxious additions; and now if either the abuſe of proſperity, or the iniquity of the late times hath added any evil quality to any of our Eccleſiaſticall things, or made us incapable of good by ſome Rite or particle of the Diſcipline or Liturgy, or if any defect appear to be in our former reformations, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if any of theſe have happened in any Rite of adoration (wherein is the greateſt danger;) it is not to be doubted, but that all theſe things will be carefully looked into; and whether by omiſſion, explanation or otherwiſe, the Diſcipline and Rites, by the help and bleſſing of God, ſhall be reformed according to the beſt patterns, and as ſhall moſt conduce to the godly unity and peace of the Church and Kingdome. What do I ſpeak only of future Reformation? ſeeing the deep Wiſdome, and the moſt ſincere piety of his Sacred Majeſty hath by the bleſſing of God upon his Royal indeavours, found out the beſt tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament for the healing of the preſent diſtempers, and by his gratious Declaration hath eſtabliſhed a moſt happy Interim, the fitteſt that could be deviſed for the preparing different appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions and affections unto an unity, meet to entertain the beſt form of a Chriſtian Church, which the infirmities of theſe laſt dayes of the laſt time can well bear. The Regicides
<pb facs="tcp:93080:9"/>of late had proceeded far in breaking down this our Houſe of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 6.7.</note> with their iron tooles, their Axes and Hammers, but as it is ſaid of King <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, that there was neither Hammer nor Axe nor any toole of iron heard while it was in building, ſo our bleſſed <hi>Solomon</hi> in reedifying this decayed houſe of God, doth the work without all iron inſtruments, without all unpleaſing ſounds, it goeth on <hi>ſenſim ſine ſenſu,</hi> and it is and will be the glorious effect of his Majeſties incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable providence, guided by the moſt gratious direction of God, <hi>cunctando reſtituiſſe rem.</hi> But ſome of them which will read this ſmall tractate, may therein obſerve ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which ſuppoſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> without the benefit of any proceedings of his Majeſty towards her reſtauration, and may therefore be ready to cenſure the Author as he well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, if he had not this juſt Apology, namely, That he can make it good by many witneſſes of worthy perſons of known in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity that this treatiſe was ready written five months agon at the leaſt, at which time the Author could only write of the ſtate and condition of things as they were then, and not as they would be in times to come. If any object, It had been better, if ever, to have publiſhed this at that time, for which it ſeemes more convenient; to which I ſay, That the Conſcience of mine own infirmities retarded and had almoſt hindred the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>But partly my deſire to contribute my poor mite towards the reſtauration of Gods Houſe prevailed with me, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the truth of that ſaying of <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that the ſcience of preaching is in a manner Angelical, and whether it be exerciſed by the tongue or hand (writing) profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth either way, and knowing my ſelf to be not far from the time when the ſtrength of voyce may decreaſe, I thought it not amiſs to put it to the trial by this beginning; whether I might
<pb facs="tcp:93080:9"/>hereafter with any hope of acceptance and profit, attempt to recompence the defect which (if I live) may likely happen in my voyce, with the labour and pains of preaching by the pen. Some may think that I have made no good choiſe in preferring the judgment of St. <hi>Hierome</hi> a Preſbyter, and not well affected, (as many think) to Epiſcopacy, before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>Epiphanius</hi> a Biſhop, and the elder of the two.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aerius</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that neither the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were, nor the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches could law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the preferment of a Biſhop above the Preſbyters, and therefore he departed from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Catholick Church, and became an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</note> Firſt, I muſt deny that <hi>Hierome</hi> was diſaffected to good Biſhops, or to the Epiſcopal dignity. His works do abundantly teſtify, that he bad in ſingular honour, both the one and the other: only he often reproveth, and that ſharply the Ambition, Covetuouſneſs, and other vices of many Biſhops, which not he only, but others before him, and in his time, even Biſhops themſelves did performe with no leſs ſharpneſs and ſeverity. See one among others, <hi>Gregory,</hi> who was created Biſhop of <hi>Saſimis,</hi> executed his function in <hi>Nazianzum,</hi> and after was advanced to the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> this Arch-Biſhop wiſheth there were no prerogative of the Throne, nor Prelacy, which (ſaith he) had indeed in former times been deſired of good and prudent men, but which now to ſhunne, is counted an act of ſingular prudence. What? is this wiſe and holy Arch-Biſhop for the abrogation of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy root and branch? no; no, he only taxeth the exorbitancy, the abuſe, the ambition, and not the holy function: he expounds himſelf, when in the ſame place he expreſſeth the prelacy which he wiſheth outed, to be the Tyrannie of Authority, and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence; it is that which cauſed many wife men to ſhun the function, becauſe in had company it is difficult to rule well, which at all times is the work of an excelling faculty,<note place="margin">Greg. Niz. in Apolog, <hi>1.</hi> In orat. ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, Baſilia praeſente.</note> and it many times happens (ſaith the ſame Father) that grace it ſelf begets Pride, and then we know that the corruption of the beſt is the worſt. Secondly, <hi>Hierome</hi> was not inferiour in
<pb facs="tcp:93080:10"/>learning, eloquence and piety to any of the Ancients, neither did any excell him in the knowledg of the antiquities of the Church. And he, that doth not look very narrowly into the works of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> may find him defective in this laſt. <hi>Hierome's</hi> teſtimony concerning the originall of Epiſcopacy, although in formall expreſſions it differs from <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s, yet perhaps by the diſtinction of extraordinary and ordinary Epiſcopacy, the difference in words may be brought into an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſenſe; and if there be a difference in the ſenſe between them: Yet <hi>Hierome</hi> affords a more immediate, direct, and efficacious argument for Epiſcopacy and its contiruance then the other. I am much deceived, and have Croſsed mine own reſolution, if I have not delivered the truth impartially, as I found it in the holy old Doctors. And although a lover of the Preſbytery may diſlike ſome paſſage of this little book ſingly conſidered, and a lover of Epiſcopacy diſlike ſome other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in like ſort apprehended; yet I have good hope that, when both have read the whole, and layed before them the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſeries of the diſcourſe, they may ſee good reaſon to like well in the whole, what they diſliked apart, and by it ſelf conſidered, and will candidly acknowledg that every thing therein tends to the ſame good end which both profeſs to ayme at.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of the Primitive Epiſcopacy, Liturgies, Rights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T having pleaſed God to chooſe for himſelf out of ſinful men a peculiar people to ſet forth his glorious praiſes, he never left the world deſtitute of heavenly inſtitutions and Laws, whereby men might be tranſlated from the ſtate of ſin and miſery, to the ſtate of holineſs and Salvation, and be made and preſerved anſwerable in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to the bleſſed condition of their tranſlation and change.</p>
            <p>Theſe willing and obedient people addicted to the Service of Almighty God, were, are, and will be by him reputed, his houſe, Family, and Kingdome, which therefore cannot be imagined to be without order and rule, without ſome certain perſons ſet apart to teach the Divine Laws, and execute other Divine inſtitutions, and with conſent of the concerned, to make Eccleſiaſtical Ordinances, which times, places, and other circumſtances require, agreeable to the Divine, and ſubſervient to the due and moſt decent execution of them.</p>
            <p>Of the number of theſe teachers and rulers of Gods houſe were, <hi>Adam, Noah, Abraham,</hi> and other heads of numerous Families unto the time of the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes;</hi> after the Law, partly fit perſons of the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> partly the Prophets, partly men bred in the Schools of the Prophets, and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, performed the Divine and Eccleſiaſtical functions unto the time of our Saviours Baptiſm: after which time he himſelf the Builder and Maſter of the houſe and Family, (whoſe ſervants and under-officers all other rulets acknowledge themſelves to be, deriving from him not onely their authority, but alſo all their abilities,
<pb facs="tcp:93080:11"/>whereby they are made able in any meaſure to fulfill the holy offices) he (I ſay) in his own perſon and in our nature, was pleaſed to execute ſuch parts of his own inſtitutions as he ſaw convenient for himſelf to perform, and to chooſe, beſides ſeventy Diſciples, twelve other men to be his Apoſtles and Miniſters of the heavenly doctrine, and annexed ceremonies.</p>
            <p>It appeareth, that it was the intention of our Saviour, that the number of twelve Apoſtles ſhould be his primary inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in founding the Original Churches of Chriſt, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of all other Churches to ſucceed unto the end of the world; It was alſo his purpoſe to make them parents of all other Miniſters which ſhould ſucceed in an ordinary courſe; which is hereby manifeſt, becauſe Chriſt promiſed to be with them unto the worlds end, which cannot be verified of their perſons, and therefore is to be underſtood of them in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their ſucceſſors, proceeding from them by ſucceſſive ordination,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil.</hi> conſtit. Monaſt. <hi>c. 22.</hi> &amp; <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Epiſt. ad <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> hom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and repreſented in their perſons; wherefore the ordination of the Apoſtles, was in ſome ſort the ordination of their ſucceſſors, and their miſſion to teach and baptize, was a virtual or legal miſſion of the other.</p>
            <p>There were three Editions of the covenant of grace, the one from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſecond from him to our Saviour, the third from our Saviour unto the end of the world. In every of theſe, the ſubſtance and kernel of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was, and is the ſame, the difference is in remarkable accidents and circumſtances; the Miniſters of the heavenly Doctrine in the firſt and ſecond, preached Chriſt to come, and had the Spirit accompanying the word, and ſeals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant miniſtred by them, as an incident annexed by Almighty God to their ordination: but yet ſo, as the ſpirit was ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily given in a leſſer meaſure to the miniſtery of the firſt, then or the ſecond Edition; The Apoſtles were in their call to the Apoſtleſhip before the death of our Saviour ordained miniſters of the third Edition of the Covenant, becauſe Chriſt was now come in the fleſh, and had begun to publiſh the great Salvation, and therefore they had a proportionable increaſe of the ſpirit added to their miniſtery, for the working of repentance, faith, and holineſs in men above the ordinary meaſure granted to the miniſtery of the ſecond Edition.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93080:11"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding that the Miniſters of the firſt and ſecond Edition of the Covenant of grace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</note> had a power of binding and looſing, in having the ſpirit accompanying their office and ſervice, and that the Apoſtles in the mortal life of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, had the ſame in a higher degree; yet the promiſe made to the confeſſion of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> of giving unto him a power of binding and looſing with the Keyes of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was not in vaine, as of a thing which he had already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; for he had received the ſame onely in the meaſure and degree meet to be diſpenſed at that time, and not in the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary fulneſs promiſed to the miniſters of the new Teſtament, fully confirmed by the death and reſurrection of Chriſt: and therefore our Saviour after his riſing again from the dead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them that promiſed fulneſs of the Spirit, which was in ordinary to accompany their miniſtery of the word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in <hi>2 Cor.</hi> hom. <hi>6.</hi> Conc. Foroju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienſ. an. <hi>791. c. 13. Athanaſ.</hi> dicta &amp; interpret. parabol. S. Script.</note> ſacraments and cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> breathing upon them and ſaying, <hi>receive ye the Holy Ghoſt, whoſeſoever ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whoſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained;</hi> hence it is, that the miniſtery of the new Teſtament fully confirmed, is in an eminent way the miniſtery of the ſpirit, and ſo called; and hence it is that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that the weapons of our war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fare are not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down reaſonings and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This meaſure of the Spirit going along and operating in the miniſterial preaching, prayer, baptiſing, bleſſing, abſolving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was now very neceſſary, as in other reſpects, ſo in this, that the world that had been ſo long captivated by Sathan, and mightily habituated in all ſinful ways,<note place="margin">Semen Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Chriſti cum in animam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis inciderit per gradus ſuos creſcit-tam diu in ancipiti eſt, quamdiu pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit. Hierom. in Epiſt. ad <hi>Gal. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> might be converted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and preſerved in his grace.</p>
            <p>Some will ſay, why are not all hearers of the Goſpel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted? to which it is ſoon anſwered, that the Holy Spirit worketh in all them that hear the Goſpel preached to them, yet gradually; firſt, that they may co-work, and then that they may continue co-working, until the work of ſaving faith be perfected in them. He gives an eat able to hear, to the hearers he gives ability to underſtand, and gives ability in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93080:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome degree to will the good, and where the good is willed, he hath given the will and the deed; and where the Good we are enabled to underſtand and Will, is not underſtood or Willed, that comes from the natural corrupted freedome of mans will, which the ſpirit doth not take away againſt our will, becauſe he will not deſtrey his own work; namely, that good natural freedome of will, conferred upon man in his creation, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being a ſubject of good or evil.</p>
            <p>A perſon not ordained to the holy miniſtery may in time and place teach and exhort with a ſpeech no leſs Orthodox, whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and perſwaſive, then any ordained miniſter of the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel can uſe, and yet it muſt be acknowledged to be far inferior in its operation tending to true edification, then the ſpeech of a miniſter ſeeming leſs perſwaſive; becauſe this is alwayes accompanied with the ſpirit, the other is not, but ſuppoſeth ſome grace in the hearer which it ſtirreth: or if it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a quickning or healing grace, it is of Gods mere indulgence, and not by vertue of Gods ordinary conſtitution and promiſe; and therefore the ſpirit going with the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the miniſter doth alwayes edifie or is reſiſted; and ſo the word preached by him is a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh; to the one the favour of death unto death, and to the other the ſavour of life unto life.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles all this while had not received the gradual complement of the gifts ordained to be beſtowed upon the miniſters of the new Teſtament;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> it was meet that Chriſt ſhould in our entire nature open heaven and enter into it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fulneſs of the ordinary or extraordinary gifts ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient for the right uſing of the Keyes of Heaven, ſhould be granted to his Vicegerents upon earth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore after his opening and poſſeſſion of Heaven, he gave thoſe gifts unto men, both extraordinary in the Apoſtles, Evangeliſts and Prophets, and ordinary, in the Paſtors and Doctors.</p>
            <p>The firſt ordinary Paſtors, received their ordination from the Apoſtles; of the Apoſtles we know no other ordination then Chriſts immediate calling of them to that office, in which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93080:12"/>they were by the foreſaid degrees perfected; the Paſtors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Apoſtles ordination their ſeminal or virtual or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination (as was ſaid) to their function, which received its perfection of degrees in the effuſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Comments upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that it was lawful at the firſt for Laicks and Deacons to preach in the Aſſemblies and Baptize; yet of that his aſſertion he brings no ſound proof; <hi>Philip</hi> was ordained a Deacon, and he baptiſed the Eunuch; <hi>Ananias</hi> a Diſciple baptiſed <hi>Saul,</hi> after called <hi>Paul;</hi> did <hi>Ananias</hi> do ſo onely in the capacity of a Diſciple, and the other onely in the capacity of a Deacon? No ſurely; for it appears that they had an immediate miſſion from God to teach and baptiſe, which is equivalent to an ordination, to the office of a Paſtor, either as to thoſe acts onely, and for that time only, or as to the whole paſtoral function to be conſtantly exerciſed. If any examples be found in the Acts of the Apoſtles of any Laicks or Deacons performing paſtoral offices, whoſe ordination ordinary or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary is not mentioned, its meeter to judge and beleive, that they had either the ordinary call or the extraordinary, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the examples of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> (when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary cannot be proved) then to affirm that any lay-man might then at his pleaſure exerciſe the acts of that ſacred vocation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> was no ſooner a Chriſtian, but he was inſtantly by Chriſts immediate appointment made an Apoſtle (<hi>Act.</hi> 9.15, 20. <hi>cum Gal.</hi> 1.16, 17, 23.) and without any other ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preached the Goſpel of Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.7.</note> yet ſome years after he together with <hi>Barnabas</hi> were by the expreſs command of the Holy Ghoſt ordained by certain Prophets and Doctors which then were at <hi>Antioch.</hi> In which ordination two things are obſervable. Firſt, that the Apoſtles were ordained by their inferiors in office; but the extraordinary commiſſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this was done, makes an exception confirming the rule, which is, that without all contradiction, the leſs is bleſſed of the greater.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.7.</note> The ſecond thing to be conſidered in that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation are the ſacred ceremonies uſed in the ordination of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, to wit, prayer, which is the principal; faſting to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93080:13"/>commend the prayer, and impoſition of hands, as a viſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Gods bleſſing them and their miniſtery with the gift of the ſpirit to accompany their ſervice to the looſing of men from the guilt and power of ſin, and ſetting of them at liberty, to walk in the wayes of Gods commandements.</p>
            <p>An ordination of Paſtors celebrated without any one of theſe ceremonies, cannot be accounted right and regular: St. <hi>Paul</hi> with other who were Presbyters ordained <hi>Timothy</hi> by the joint impoſition of his and their hands; we find impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands placed by the Apoſtle among the fundamentals of Chriſtian Religion;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14. <hi>cum</hi> 2 Tim. 1.6. Heb. 6.1, 2.</note> and there, although it followeth the immerſions in the names of the bleſſed Trinity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may ſeem to import confirmation; yet it need not denote confirmation alone, but any other perpetual ordinance of God, wherein this ceremony was to be uſed, by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Apoſtles exampled and practiſe.</p>
            <p>They which ſay that this ceremony was to laſt no longer in uſe then God was pleaſed to continue the miraculous opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions uſual in the Apoſtolick times, ſeem to impute inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs to the Apoſtle, in reckoning that one of the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Religion, which was not to be perpetually conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the militant Church: but we are aſſured, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle being moved by the Holy Ghoſt, could not ſpeak incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately, and that every fundamental of Chriſtian Religion, ſhall continue in Chriſts Church unto the end of the world, as this ceremony both in confirmation and in ordinations of Paſtors hath hitherto been alwayes uſed in the univerſal Church, and without doubt will ſo continue unto the end of time.</p>
            <p>Paſtors are called in the Apoſtolical Epiſtles by two other names,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</note> that is, Biſhops and Presbyters; the Apoſtleſhip con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it ſelf the paſtoral offices, and therefore an Apoſtle was alſo called a Biſhop and Presbyter. The firſt mention of Paſtors by the name of Presbyters of Elders, is in <hi>Acts</hi> 11.30. where the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> is ſaid to have ſent relief by <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> unto the Elders of the Churches in <hi>Judaea,</hi> in the time of the great dearth, which was in the days of <hi>Claudius Caeſar;</hi> in the 15 Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, we finde
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93080:13"/>the controverſie concerning the neceſſity of circumciſion and keeping of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> brought by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> before the Apoſtles and Elders or Presbyters in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be by them determined: We ſee in the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> how that <hi>Paul</hi> with ſome of the brethren, went in unto <hi>James</hi> and all the elders were preſent; whence we may obſerve, that the Apoſtles did not diſcuſs and end the controverſie concerning circumciſion and keeping of the Law without the preſence of the Presbyters of the Church where they then were; nor did <hi>James</hi> alone heat <hi>Paul,</hi> but together with his Presbyters did both hear him, and give him that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Councel, to purifie himſelf for the avoiding the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the beleiving Jews, which were numerous in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here ariſeth a queſtion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</note> whether St. <hi>James</hi> was head of the Presbyters of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> onely as he was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, having his ordinary reſidence in that Church, or alſo as having an ordinary authority over the Presbyters, which was to be continued to ſucceſſors over the ſucceding Presbyters; it is certain, that as an Apoſtle he was the head of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, having a ſuperiority over them; but as the Apoſtleſhip was not to paſs to ſucceſſors, ſo neither was his authority to be conveyed to any in ſucceſſion; but to be terminated with his life: it is more then probable, that at that time he was their ſuperior, onely as an Apoſtle ſettled in that Church, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had we need to conceive him in any ſubſequent times to become their head in any other ſenſe then this, if the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous teſtimony of the ancient Doctors of the Church did not conſtrain us to be of another judgment, unleſs we will reject the witneſs of the Catholick Church conſtantly perſevered in from the beginining of the ſecond Centuary after our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours birth unto this day. For the Fathers do conſtantly affirm that St. <hi>James</hi> was (for ſome time before his deceaſe) Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not onely in the ſenſe of the word [Biſhop] common to an Apoſtle and every Presbyter, but in the ſenſe which ſoon after the time of <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> was appropriated to it, that is, ſignifying ſuch a Presbyter, as had a ſuperiority over all the reſt of the Presbyters of the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93080:14"/>Church, to continue in him during life, and to be transferred to ſome other after him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> an Hiſtorian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud</hi> Euſeb. <hi>hiſs.</hi> l. 4. c. 21. <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 3. c. 29.</note> who flouriſhed about the year 170, relateth that after the death of St. <hi>James, Simon Cleopa</hi> being choſen Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> one <hi>Thebulis</hi> began to corrupt the Church with vain Doctrine, becauſe he was not made Biſhop there. And the ſame Hiſtorian writeth, that <hi>Simon Cleopa</hi> lived Biſhop of that place, until the times of <hi>Trajane</hi> the Emperor, under whoſe government <hi>Simon</hi> ſuffered Martyrdome, and <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle died; by which teſtimony of an hiſtorian who lived within 60 years after the death of the Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> it plainly appeareth, that <hi>Simon</hi> was not (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of St. <hi>James</hi> brother of our Lord) conſtituted onely a ſingle Presbyter of that Church, nor <hi>James</hi> before him head thereof only as an Apoſtle or an extraordinary gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but that both were ordinary rulers of the whole Church, as well Presbyters as the other members thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paedagog.</hi> l. 3. c. <hi>ult. Strom.</hi> 6.</note> who lived before the year of our Lord 200, makes a clear diſtinction between a Biſhop and a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaying, that in the Scriptures ſome precepts pertain to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, ſome to Presbyters, and ſome to Deacons; and in another place, that a Presbyter doing and teaching according to Gods will, although he be not on earth honoured with the firſt chair, ſhall ſit on the 24 thrones judging the people: and a little after he ſaith, that here in the Church the provections or proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Biſhops, Presbyters, Deacons, be imitations of the angelical glory. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who flouriſhed in the year of our Lord 200,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Monoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> c. 11.</note> mentions an uſe in his time of asking leave of the Biſhop, of the Presbyters, and of the Deacons to marry: Elſewhere he calls upon the Hereticks to ſhew the beginnings of their Churches, and ſo to reckon the order of their Biſhops, running from the beginning by ſucceſſions, that the firſt (Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop) have an Apoſtle or an Apoſtolical man for his auctor or anteceſſor, as the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> relates <hi>Polycarpus</hi> to be placed there Biſhop by <hi>John</hi> (the Apoſtle;) and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> reporteth <hi>Clement</hi> to have been ordained there by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adverſus Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentin.</hi> c. 4.</note>) In another place the ſame author ſaith, that <hi>Valentinus</hi> becauſe he was ingenious &amp; eloquent had hoped
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93080:14"/>an Epiſcopacy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Baptiſmo.</hi> c. 17.</note> and being angry that another by prerogative of Martyrdome had obtained it, he departed from the Church. In another place he hath this obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi> the emulation of Epiſcopacy is the mother of Schiſmes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adverſus hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 3. <hi>&amp; apud</hi> Euſeb. l. 5. c. 18.</note> I muſt not forget the teſtimony of <hi>Ireaaeus,</hi> who affirmeth of himſelf, that he was a hearer of <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who was not onely taught by the Apoſtles, and converſed with many of them which ſaw the Lord, but was alſo by the Apoſtles in <hi>Aſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adverſ. haereſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 3. <hi>Edit. Pariſ.</hi> 1567.</note> (in which is the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi>) conſtituted a Biſhop: the ſame <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth enumerate the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> which ſucceeded one another from <hi>Peter</hi> unto <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> who was the twelfth ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of <hi>Peter. Polycrates</hi> (who was 65 years in the Lord when he wrote his Epiſtle unto <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning the time of the celebration of the Pàſche, which was about the year of our Lord 197, whereby it appeareth, that he began to flouriſh about 50 years after the death of <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, if not much ſooner (if he was come to years of diſcretion before his Baptiſm;) <hi>Polycrates</hi> (I ſay) who was ſo near the times of the Apoſtles ſaith, that he was the eighth Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Now it is acknowledged by all, that in the time of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor,</hi> a Biſhop had the preheminence over the Presbyters in every Church; and therefore it is conſequent, that <hi>Polycrates</hi> by the ſeven Biſhops preceding him in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> meaneth not ſingle Presbyters, but ſuch Biſhops as were in the Church at the time of his writing that Epiſtle to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the principality of the Eccleſiaſtical regiment had been in the Colledge of Presbyters; until the death of the Apoſtles, and after their deceaſe the principality of that government was committed to one, and not before; ſurely <hi>Polycrates, Irenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> had egregiouſly prevaticated in attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the principality of one to ſome part of the time of the Apoſtles, which (they living with thouſands who muſt have ſeen and conſented to that change made after the Apoſtles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, if any ſuch had been then firſt made,) could not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. But that theſe holy men were not unfaithful in their relation, doth evidently appear by this; namely, that all the Fathers, none contradicting, agree with them, affirming Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops having in an ordinary way a ſuperiority over Presbyters,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93080:15"/>to have been ordained in the times of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Concerning Arch-biſhops,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect</hi> 6.</note> (omitting the gueſſes of ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Doctors concerning the Archiepiſcopacy of <hi>Mark, Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi>) we may find ſome intimation of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the end of the ſecond century, partly, by the act of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in his attempt to excommunicate the Churches of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and partly by a paſſage in <hi>Tertullian,</hi> where he ſaith, the Biſhop of Biſhops hath made a decree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but certain it is, that before the year of our Lord 250, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> flouriſhed,<note place="margin">l. de pudicitia c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Arch-biſhops were ordained in the Church: For <hi>Cyprian</hi> writeth, that there were many years and a long age ſince many Biſhops convening under <hi>Agryppinus</hi> (Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi>) decreed,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. ad Cornel. l. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in one of his Epiſtles to <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he ſaith, that his adverſaries boaſted, ſaying, that twenty five Biſhops of <hi>Numidia</hi> would come to <hi>Carthage,</hi> who would make unto themſelves a Biſhop there.</p>
            <p>Among theſe Arch-biſhops, (who were ſuch indeed, but not yet in name, that we can find in any approved auctor of that age) were ſome more eminent then other; each of which had ſome Arch-biſhops ſubordinate to them, which in following times were called primates: for in a province was one chief City, under which were divers mother Cities, which had leſſer Cities under them; In theſe were the Biſhops, in the Mother-cities were the Metropolitans or Arch-biſhops, in the firſt, the Primates; priviledges made ſome variations.</p>
            <p>Of Primates and Metropolitans, the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> ſaith, it is manifeſt, that, if any be ordained without the will and conſcience of the Metropolitane Biſhop, this great and holy Council hath decreed, he ought not to be a Biſhop. And in another Canon, the ancient manner (or cuſtome) doth laſt in <hi>Egypt, Lybia</hi> and <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> that the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> have the power of all theſe; for the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath a like cuſtome, in like manner alſo at <hi>Antioch</hi> and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: let the due honour proper to every Church be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to it. Theſe Primates and Arch-biſhops had no power in things proper to the cognizance of a Biſhop in his own Dioceſs, but onely in thoſe things whereof the Canons of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93080:15"/>the Church had committed to them the hearing and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or which were of concernment to many <hi>Dioceſſes:</hi> And this is it which <hi>Cyprian</hi> meaneth, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> none of us (Biſhops) doth conſtitute himſelf to be a Biſhop of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or doth compell this Colledge by tyrannical terror to the neceſſity of obeying, ſeeing every Biſhop hath according to his own liberty and free will, that he may not be judged by another. <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Apud Vopiſum in Saturnino.</note> who reigned from the year of our Lord 117, to the year 135, writeth in a certain Epiſtle hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible untruths againſt Chriſtians; as that there was never a Presbyter of the Chriſtians which was not a Mathematician, a Southſayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that the very Patriarch, when he came to <hi>Egypt,</hi> was by ſome compelled to adore <hi>Serapis,</hi> by others to adore Chriſt; that they, which ſaid themſelves to be Biſhops of Chriſt, were devoted to <hi>Serapis.</hi> It ſeems this Emperour had taken notice, that Chriſtians had Eccleſiaſtical officers, whereof ſome were-called Presbyters, ſome called Biſhops, and (perhaps) that the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> was over all <hi>Egypt, &amp;c.</hi> and Biſhops thereof; and therefore calls him by the name of a like civil Magiſtrate, (Patriarch,) which was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward uſed by Chriſtians in a like ſenſe: but too much hath been ſaid to ſhew that it was ordained in the times of the Apoſtles, that the principal authority in every Church ſhould be in one Presbyter advanced above and over the reſt, unto whom in a ſhort time after, the name of (Biſhop) was made proper. This truth is ſo clear and written, as it were, with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital or uncial letters in the writings of all the ancients, that he that runneth may read it in them.</p>
            <p>In the next place it ſhould be conſidered, whether that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance conſtituting Epiſcopacy made in the Apoſtolical times, was not, in proper ſenſe, an Apoſtolical conſtitution;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</note> and if ſo, whether therefore it be unalterable? But that this matter may be better underſtood, it is convenient firſt to ſpeak of the Authority and Power given to the Biſhop, what it was, and how ample in thoſe times.<note place="margin">De baptiſme. c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> gives us ſome information in this point, when he ſaith, that the chief Prieſt which is the (Biſhop) hath the right (or power) of giving Baptiſm; then the Presbyters and Deacons, but not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93080:16"/>without the authority of the Biſhop, for the preſervation of the honour of the Church, which remaining ſafe, peace is ſafe maintained. For the underſtanding of this, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that, where the exerciſe of the power of preaching, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in ſuch place and among ſuch perſons was not by ſome ordinance of the Church determined to this or that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Presbyter, there it pertained to the Biſhop to do it, and not to any other without his leave; yea the very Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Canons could not be made without his conſent and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as their principal author under Chriſt.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Titum. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, the whole care of the Church belongs unto the Biſhop; and therefore he was to ſee that all the Presbyters did their duties aſſigned to them, and that the miniſterial acts not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to any ſpecial Presbyter, were to be done by the Biſhop himſelf, or by him whom he would appoint to do them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hierom</hi> mentions one thing proper to a Biſhop;<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> what doth a Biſhop ſaith he (excepting Ordination,) which a Presbyter doth not do? where he maketh ordination of Presbytery to be the proper work of a Biſhop, which the Presbyters were not to perform (except perhaps in the Biſhops place, and by his commiſſion in ſome caſes of neceſſity) as ſhall be ſhewed hereafter; not that the Presbyters had no hand in Ordination, but that the principal act in it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 3.</note> was onely the Biſhops. For the fourth Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Sed ſola propter auctoritatem ſummo ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot o Clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratio reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vata eſt, ne a multis Eccleſiae Diſciplina ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicata concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam ſolveret, Scandala ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neventur. Iſid. de Eccl. offic. c. <hi>7.</hi> Can. <hi>5.</hi> circa an. <hi>656.</hi>
               </note> when a Presbyter is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, the Biſhop bleſſing him and holding his hand upon his head, let the Presbyters alſo which be preſent, lay their hands by the hand of the Biſhop upon his head. And it follows in the fourth Canon: when a Deacon is ordained, let the Biſhop alone which bleſſeth him, lay his hand upon his head, becauſe he is not conſecrated to the Prieſthood, but to a Service. Where we are to obſerve, that the impoſition of the hands of the Presbyters, is a condition antecedent requiſite to the conſecration of a Presbyter, and ſo proper to it, that it may not be uſed in the ordination of a Deacon, much leſs of any other inferior officer; the bleſſing is the act in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dination, which is appropriated to the Biſhop. And therefore in the ſecond Council of <hi>Hiſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis,</hi> the Presbyters and Deacons conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by a Biſhop, who having ſore eyes could not read,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93080:16"/>were depoſed from the degrees which they had ill gotten; a presbyter having contrary to the order of the Church read the benediction.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop performed in the Church the chief offices of preaching and adminiſtration of the Communion, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, none other being to do either in his preſence, but by his call: ſometime to ſhew his power, or out of envy, idleneſs, or diſdain, he neither would himſelf exhort the people, nor require a presbyter to do it.<note place="margin">ad Nepotianum de vita clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Which great fault <hi>Hierom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves; in ſome Churches (ſaith he) is a bad cuſtome, that the Biſhop being preſent, the presbyters hold their peace, as though the Biſhop envied or diſdained to hear them.</p>
            <p>Some other things were in ſome ſort appropriated to the Biſhop, but were not made ſo peculiar to him as ordination was; nor were they all of them ſo ancient priviledges, nor of that weight; for confirmation was the chiefeſt of them,<note place="margin">Greg. Epiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> Ep. <hi>26.</hi> Conc. Carth. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>32.</hi> Pſeudambroſ. in Ep. ad Eph. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> which in ſome caſes and places presbyters might and did uſually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: The making of the Chriſm, the ſigning of the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the forehead with the ſign of the Croſs, conſecration of Virgins, of the altar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were ceremonies of leſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſome of them of a latter inſtitution.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding that the Biſhop had in ſome things a propriety, and in all things Eccleſiaſtical a principality, yet the presbyters had a ſubordinate power ordinary or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in the one, and in the other; for the Biſhop could ordain no presbyter without the conſent of the presbyters, and the im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſition of their hands. <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmeth, that the Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> preſided with <hi>Cornelius</hi> their Biſhop.<note place="margin">Cyprian Ep. ad Cornelium.</note> The fourth Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage</hi> prohibits the Biſhop to hear any mans cauſe without the preſence of his Clergy, and forbids him to give,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 22. <hi>Can.</hi> 23.</note> ſell or change any thing belonging to the Church, without conſent and ſubſcription of the Clergy. And that there was not ſo great a diſtance between the Biſhop and presbyters, as hath of latter times been kept, nor as is between a presbyter and a Deacon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 34. <hi>Can.</hi> 35.</note> doth appear by ſome Canons of the ſame ancient Council, which ordain that the Biſhop ſitting in any place, ſuffer not a presbyter to ſtand: and that the Biſhop in the Church ſit among the presbyters in a higher ſeat, but in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93080:17"/>houſe muſt know himſelf to be a College (or companion) of the presbyters. Concerning the diſtance between a presbyter and Deacon, the Canons of the Synod ſay, that a Deacon is miniſter as well of the presbyter,<note place="margin">Vide Conc. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenum. c. <hi>14.</hi> &amp; Arelat. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> as of the Biſhop; that a Deacon in the convention of the presbyters may ſpeak onely when he is asked, and that he is not to ſit but when he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the presbyter.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 37. <hi>Can.</hi> 39. <hi>Can.</hi> 40.</note> Therefore it may ſeem, that if after 300 years ſince the deceaſe of the Apoſtles, (at which time the power of Biſhops was much enlarged) there was no more difference between a Biſhop and a presbyter, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was far leſſe at that time between the Biſhop and the Colledge of presbyters, then the birth of popery hath made between them.<note place="margin">Eſai. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> calls the Colledge of presbyters the Biſhops Senate; intimating thereby, that the Biſhop ought to hear and determine Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, in the preſence, and with the adviſe and conſent of his presbyters. Hence it was, that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 22.</note> long before the time of St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> the holy Martyr <hi>Cyprian</hi> (having with conſent of the Clergy of the place where he then was (being abſent from his own City and presbyters) ordained one a reader, and another a ſubdeacon, he) excuſeth himſelf by his Letters to the Presbyters of his own Cathedral, ſaying, that nothing new was done by him in their abſence, but what was begun in their Common Council, was promoted by urgent neceſſity; their Council therefore that was requiſite in ſo ſmall a matter, was much more neceſſary in matters of greateſt weight.</p>
            <p>It is opportune here to conſider the famous queſtion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the firſt twenty years of the Apoſtles preaching (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more or leſs) the whole care of the Church did in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon belong to the Colledge of presbyters of every Church where no Apoſtle was preſent, nor Evangeliſt, nor any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the place of an Apoſtle; or did the care and government of every Church (except where ſome invincible hindrance withſtood) belong unto one as principal and head, and to the presbyters onely as his Senate and Counſellors?</p>
            <p>The Ancients vary in this point:<note place="margin">Contra haereſ. Aerii.</note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and ſome others affirm, that the office of a Biſhop was inſtituted by the Apoſtles, diſtinct from the offices of the Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, prophets,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93080:17"/>and presbyters;<note place="margin">Ultra ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotium non eſt gradus ordinis &amp; tamen intra hunc gradum &amp; ordmem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingit eſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctionem dignitatum &amp; officiorum, quae tamen novum gradum vel ordinem non conſtituunt, ut Archipresbyter, Epiſcopus, Archiepiſcopus, Patriarcha, pontifex ſummus, qui ultra ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium non addunt ordinem nec gradum novum ſed ſolum dignitatem &amp; officium, &amp; ita Epiſcopatus prout concernit ordinem ſacer dotti benè poteſt dici ordo, ſed prout diſtinguitur contra ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium dicitur dignitatem quandam vel officium Epiſeopi annexum, &amp; non eſt propriè nomen ordinis, nec no vus character imprimitur, nec nova poteſtas datur, ſed poteſtas data ampliatur; unde ſicut non recipit alias claves ſic nec alium ordinem: &amp; hoc ſenſit magiſter Hugo (de <hi>S.</hi> Victore) &amp; Magiſter ſententiarum. Bonavent. in <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>24.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> Et poſtea—non ita propriè dicitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis ordinari cum promovetur in Epiſcopum, ſicut cum promovetur in ſacerdotem, ſed magis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè dicitur conſecrari, &amp; poſtea—non datur ibi nova poteſtas ſed ſolùm poteſtas ligandi &amp; ſolvendi ampliatur.
<p>Solis ſacerdotibus datur &amp; in ordine ſacerdotali poteſtas clavium, ſcilicet quantum ad ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendum &amp; ligandum quaſi mediatoribus inter Deum &amp; ſubditos. Si objiciatur quod magis cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit poteſtatem clavium dart Epiſcopo in conſecratione Epiſcopi, dicendum quod nequaquam, quia Epiſcopus non dicitur novum ordinem, nec in conſecrationem Epiſcopi datur novus ordo ſed tantum ampliatur poteſtas. Alex. Halenſ. to. <hi>4.</hi> de poteſt. clavium. q. <hi>20.</hi> m. <hi>8.</hi> a.</p>
                  <p>Probatum eſt (ſcilicet diſp. <hi>140.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>) inquit Vaſques quod Hieronymus nullam conſtituat differentiam jure Divino inter Epiſcopatum &amp; Presbyterium, ſed cenſeat jure tantum eccleſiaſtico diſcrimen fuiſſe introductum. In <hi>3.</hi> p. diſp. <hi>142.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ego ſanè (inquit Vaſques) ſuſpicor vehementer <hi>S.</hi> Thomam exiſtimaſſe conſecrationem cum qua confertur poteſtas Epiſcopajis jure humano eſſe introductam. In <hi>3.</hi> p. diſp. <hi>143.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and that in all Churches where fit men for that office were found, they were ordained and ſet over the pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and that the Senate of presbyters did alone govern onely in ſome Churches where no man was found fit to be made a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hierom</hi> and ſome other taught,<note place="margin">Epiſcopes ſolae ordinatione ſuperiores eſſe Presbyteris. Chryſoſt. in <hi>1.</hi> Ep. ad Timoth. hom. <hi>11.</hi> Poſtea unus eſt gradus <hi>S.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom in <hi>1.</hi> Ep. ad Tim. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that the Apoſtles left at the firſt the whole care of every Church, (where none of them or their Vicegerents, or Evangeliſts reſided) unto the body of the presbyters of each Church, which exerciſed all Eccleſiaſtical powers in common, until the presbyters began to divide the flock, and to make of one Church many Independent Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: For the avoiding of which inconvenience, the Churches unanimouſly agreed to commit the principal care of every Church unto one presbyter, without whoſe conſent the reſt of the presbyters were not allowed to exerciſe any part of their Eccleſiaſtical function;<note place="margin">In Ep. ad Tit. c. <hi>1.</hi> vide gloſſ. diſt. <hi>23.</hi> c. legimus.</note> and to that advanced presbyter ſome miniſterial acts, and alſo the name of Biſhop were after ſome time appropriated. Before Sidings in Religion (ſaith <hi>Hierom</hi>) were made by the inſtinct of the Devil; and that it was ſaid
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93080:18"/>among the people,<note place="margin">El Amalarium de Eccleſ. offic. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Et Steph. Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſ. Epiſcopum de ſacramento altaris. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I of <hi>Apollos, &amp;c.</hi> the Churches were governed by the Common Council of the Presbyters: but after that every Presbyter thought thoſe whom he baptiſed to be his and not Chriſts, it was decreed in all the world, that one choſen out of the Presbyters ſhould be ſet over the reſt, unto whom all the care of the Church ſhould appertain; and ſo the ſeeds of Schiſmes ſhould be taken away. A little after he affirmeth, that at the firſt the care of the Church was equally divided among many; and yet a little further (having cited out of 1. Epiſt. to <hi>Tim.</hi> and the Epiſt. to <hi>Titus,</hi> and the Epiſt. to the <hi>Philipp. &amp;c.</hi>) theſe (ſaith he) were ſaid that we might ſhew, that the ancient Presbyters were the ſame with Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; but by little and little, that the plants of diſſention might be plucked up,<note place="margin">—In quos (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquentes) nonnunquam Epiſcoporum &amp; Presbyterorum cenſura deſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Hier. ad Demetriad.</note> all the ſollicitude was delated to one. Therefore as the Presbyters know themſelves by the cuſtome of the Church to be ſubject to him who is ſet over them, ſo let Biſhops know themſelves to be greater then Presbyters, more by cuſtome then by the truth of Divine diſpotiſion, and ought in common to rule the Church, imitating <hi>Moſes,</hi> who when he might have alone ruled the people, yet choſe other with whom he would judge them.</p>
            <p>The words of this ancient Father need no explication; for they ſay plainly that every Church (meaning wherein no extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary miniſter reſided, Apoſtle, or his Vicegerent) was at the firſt governed by the Colledge of Presbyters, and that their dividing one Church into many Independent Congregations,<note place="margin">Quare in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus niſi per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Epiſcopi accipiat Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctum? id factum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimus ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem potius ſacerdotii qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad legis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſalus in ſummi ſacerdotis dignitate ac veneratione conſiſtit, cui ſi non exors quaedam &amp; ab hominibus [omnibus] eminens detur poteſtas, tot in Eccleſiis efficientur ſchiſmata quot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes. Inde venit, ut ſine chriſmate &amp; Epiſcopi juſſione neque Presbyter neque Diaconus jus habeat baptizandi, quod frequenter (ſi tamen neceſſitas cogit) ſcimus licere laicis. Hier. contra Lucifer.</note> firſt (that we can find) in <hi>Corinth,</hi> after, in many other places, put a neceſſity upon the Churches to provide a convenient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt ſo dangerous a diſeaſe; which remedy was the committing of every Church to one chief miniſter, to whom the reſt were to be ſubordinate in the manner before ſpecified.</p>
            <p>Here obſerve, 1. that, according to St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> every Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ought to rule the Church in common with the presbyters. 2. that <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, that the decree of making one chief in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93080:18"/>every Church was in all the world; whereby he intimates this inſtitution of Biſhops to have its beginning after the planting of the Churches in moſt parts of the then known world. 3. that he affirmeth, that <hi>Paulatim</hi> (by little and little, or by degrees) the care of every Church was committed to one; which doth inſinuate, that the decree inſtituting a Biſhop was not in a Synod of the Apoſtles or Churches; but enacted in every Church, firſt in ſome, then in other, and in a ſhort time in all, over all the world, in ſuch manner as a general cuſtome is created; and therefore he ſaith, that the Presbyters are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Biſhop by the cuſtome of the Church, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop greater then they, rather by cuſtome then by the Lords diſpoſition. So <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing to <hi>Hierome;</hi> although (ſaith he) according to the names of honour, which the uſe (or cuſtome) of the Church hath kept, a Biſhop be greater then a presbyter, yet <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (a Biſhop) is in many things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to <hi>Hierome</hi> (a presbyter:) So modeſtly and humbly doth the moſt pious and wiſe Biſhop <hi>Auguſtine</hi> write unto the holy presbyter <hi>Hierome,</hi> his elder in years, and his inferior in dignity. They that affirm Epiſcopacy to be inſtituted by a Council, do not mean a Council taken in a proper ſenſe, but for the unanimous votes of the Churches decreeing the ſame thing upon the ſame grounds and reaſons, which are the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal things reſpected in a Council: and it is truely ſaid, <hi>illud unumquod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicitur quod eſt principalius in eo.</hi> Fourthly, it ſeems conſequent to <hi>Hierom</hi>'s above-cited diſcourſe, that it is not certain, which ſome affirm, that Biſhops were ſet over the Churches before the time wherein St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> or his Epiſtle to <hi>Titus, &amp;c.</hi> out of which <hi>Hierome</hi> proves the identity of Biſhops and presbyters, and the government of the Church by the Colledge of presbyters. But of the exact time of the inſtitution of Biſhops it's not much material to know, ſeeing all agree, it was made in the time of the Apoſtles. By ſome of thoſe places cited by him, it's likely he intended onely to prove the name Biſhop to be common at that time as well to presbyters as to their ſuperior Eccleſiaſtical officers.</p>
            <p>But it might be thought that <hi>Hierome</hi> in this matter contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93080:19"/>himſelf,<note place="margin">In cataloge Scriptorum Eccleſ. in Jacobe.</note> becauſe elſewhere he ſaith, that <hi>James</hi> the brother of our Lord was <hi>ſtatim</hi> (quickly) after our Lords paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ordained by the Apoſtles Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that he ruled that Church for 30 years, until the ſeventh year of <hi>Nero:</hi> unto this difficulty another may be added, ſhewing a ſeeming contrariety in this learned Father's ſpeeches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inſtitution of Biſhops; which is, that here he affirmeth the Epiſcopacy to be an Eccleſiaſtical and ſo an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſtitution, and in another place that it is an Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal tradition. It is not hard to reconcile theſe ſeeming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary expreſſions:<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grium.</note> for firſt, we muſt conſider Epiſcopacy or government by one as chief among the presbyters, to have been either extraordinary, (managed by one extraordinary perſon, which was not by any ordinary rule of the Church to have a ſucceſſour,) or ordinary, in the hand of one perſon, which, by a Canon of the Church, was to have a ſucceſſour: an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preſent in any Church had power over the presbyters, and the preheminence in all ſacerdotal duties above them in that Church. Of Apoſtles ſome were primary, as the twelve, other ſecondary; and theſe were either indeed (as well as in name) A poſtles, or onely becauſe they were converſant with the Apoſtles and their helpers, and many times left by them in ſome Churches, or ſent to them as their Vicegerents, ſuch were <hi>Timothy, Titus, Linus, Clemens, &amp;c.</hi> all theſe by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical function, or by vertue of their Vicegerency, had the principal rule in the Churches wherein they abode, even then, when in all other Churches, the Colledge of the presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters took the care of all, having no Superior conſtantly reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent over them. Afterward, when upon occaſion of the presbyters abuſing their power by reaſon of the Apoſtles ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to the be getting of Schiſmes, the Churches by Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical conſent agreed to give in every Church a principality to one presbyter above the reſt (which in ſome time after had the name of (Biſhop) made proper to him, and was made an ordinary officer in all Churches;) then the Apoſtles and their Vicegerents in the Churches of their reſidence had the power over the Colledge of presbyters, not onely by their Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Vicegerency, but alſo by the new decree, and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93080:19"/>of an ordinary Epiſcopacy. Now, becauſe it was thought fit by the Apoſtles that <hi>James</hi> ſhould reſide at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (and that not long after the aſcenſion of our Saviour) it might truly be ſaid, that he was then ordained, that is, conſtituted Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (extraordinary) in that place for ſome particular reaſons taken from conſideration of ſome particular condition of that place, whoſe Epiſcopacy afterward was continued for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reaſon of preventing Schiſmes; and conſequently of an extraordinary Epiſcopacy was made an ordinary Epiſcopacy, which was to paſs to ſucceſſors. The ſame proportionably muſt be ſaid of the Epiſcopacy of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> of <hi>Timothy</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> of <hi>Linus</hi> and <hi>Clemens</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo of others: all of which were firſt Biſhops ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and after the general decree they were alſo made as ordinary Biſhops in the Churches where the decree found them extraordinary Biſhops. <hi>Hierom</hi> doth in many places ſpeak as one that ſuppoſed Biſhops to be above Presbyters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of that decree; but his meaning was not, that ordinary Biſhops were before it (for then he had contradicted himſelf) but the extraordinary.</p>
            <p>If the reſt of the Fathers be ſo underſtood (as it is not very improbable but that many of them may) the ſeeming diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him and ſome of them may be perhaps in the main reconciled. <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith, that Biſhops in the life time of the Apoſtles were called Apoſtles, the name of the extraordinary Biſhops being alſo communicated to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Biſhops, who alſo had ſome appearance of being Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents unto thoſe twelve general Paſtors of the univerſal Church while they lived, as they were counted their ſucceſſors after their deceaſe.</p>
            <p>As to the other ſeeming contrariety in St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s writings affirming the ordinary Epiſcopacy to be of Eccleſiaſtical and humane inſtitution and alſo of Apoſtolical tradition, it is eaſily anſwered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the ordinary Epiſcopacy is not a primary tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles but of the Churches; to whoſe decree the Apoſtolical approbation added no new ſanction, but ratified the authority of the Churches as prudently exerciſed in making that conſtitution.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93080:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, that decree may be ſaid to be of Apoſtolical tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, becauſe their extraordinary Epiſcopacy and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Epiſcopacy of their Vicegerents eſtabliſhed by them, were patterns, which the Churches had an eye unto for their direction and encouragement in the framing of that decree; hoping that the good of peace, preſerved where the extraordinary Epiſcopacy was placed, would be beſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in all Churches when the like government ſhould be ſetled in all to continue by ſucceſſion.<note place="margin">3.</note> Thirdly, the ancient Fathers affirm many eccleſiaſtical obſervances to be of divine or Apoſtolical inſtitution or tradition, upon other grounds then may beget a certain belief of their being truely divine or Apoſtolical. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that whatſoever the univerſal Church holdeth, and is not found in following Councils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, but always retained, is moſt rightly believed to be delivered by the Apoſtolick authority.<note place="margin">De bapt. contra Donatiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>4.</hi> c. ult.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> affirmeth, that many things, which are by tradition obſerved in the Churches, have uſurped to themſelves the authority of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine law; as in baptiſm, to immerge the head thrice, and then to taſt the concord of milk and honey,<note place="margin">Adverſus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferianos.</note> to ſignifie infancy: and on the Lords day, and in all the Pentecoſt not to pray kneeling nor to faſt. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great exhorteth all to embrace the decree of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council concerning the ſet time of the celebration of the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> as a gift of God, and a Commandement ſent down from heaven:<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtantini. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> Edit. Baſil. <hi>1570.</hi>
               </note> for whatſoever is decreed in the holy Councils of Biſhops, that ought to be aſcribed to the divine will. <hi>Hierom</hi> in another place ſaith, let every one judge the precepts of the ancients to be Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical laws.<note place="margin">Hierom. Ep. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> It is not to be doubted (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>) but that every Chriſtian obſervance is of divine erudition; and that whatſoever is received by the Church into a cuſtome of devotion,<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>2.</hi> de je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jun. Pentecoſt.</note> proceeded from the Apoſtolick tradition, and the Doctrine of the holy Spirit. The Fathers uſe very frequently to affirm ſome inſtitutions or rites to be divine or Apoſtolical, becauſe they ſeemed a greeable to, and their lawfulneſs demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable by, the old Teſtament, the Goſpels, or Apoſtolick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles: So the Lent Faſt is by them ſaid to be of Apoſtolical and Divine tradition, becauſe it ſeems an imitation of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93080:20"/>Faſt of <hi>Elias</hi> and of Chriſt; and Monachiſm is affirmed to be Apoſtolick, becauſe it hath an appearance of being an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt,<note place="margin">Amalar. Alcuin. Pontifical. Damaſ.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet many ancient writers make Pope <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> (who flouriſhed Forty years after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle) to be the author of the <hi>Quadrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimal</hi> Faſt (although indeed it had a much later beginning,) and affirm <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Anthony</hi> to be the Fathers of Monachiſm. So that many inſtitutes were counted Apoſtolick, becauſe ſome example or reaſon of the Scripture did ſeem to warrant them. Whence <hi>Hierom</hi> and others intimate,<note place="margin">Hierom. in vita Pauli.</note> that Epiſcopacy was inſtituted in imitation of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, or of the Apoſtles and 70 Diſciples, affirming Biſhops to be ſucceſſors of <hi>aaron,</hi> and the Apoſtles and Presbyters the ſucceſſors of the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> and of the 70 Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is a certain truth, acknowledged by all the learned, that the Apoſtles were authors as well of local and temporary or univerſal and temporary ordinances, rites, or ceremonies, as of univerſal and perpetual: for they were inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt infallibly to diſcern both what the preſent condition (although variable) of ſome or all the Churches required, and what upon reaſons ariſing from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variable grounds and circumſtances was needful to be obſerved in all the Churches of Chriſt: <hi>Polycarpus</hi> (a hearer of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and by St. <hi>John</hi> made Biſhop of <hi>Smyrna</hi>) celebrated the Paſche in the fourteenth moon, and ſo did the reſt of <hi>Aſia</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Eaſt:</hi> obſerving it the ſame time with the <hi>Jews,</hi> moved thereto by the countenance and example of St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle; but <hi>Anicetus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (who flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the life time of <hi>Polycarpus</hi>) and generally the Churches of the <hi>Weſt;</hi> kept the Feaſt at another time, and on the Lords day, induced thereto as they affirmed by the tradition and example of St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle. We cannot with reaſon and charity think that either <hi>Polycarpus</hi> with the <hi>Aſians</hi> and <hi>Eaſt,</hi> or <hi>Anicetus</hi> with the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches,<note place="margin">Apud Euſeb. &amp; Iren.</note> could be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the time when <hi>Peter</hi> in the <hi>Weſt</hi> or <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Aſia</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that Feaſt, <hi>Polycarpus</hi> being an eye witneſs of what the Apoſtle St. <hi>John</hi> did, and <hi>Anicetus</hi> being a hearer of the hearers of <hi>Clemens,</hi> who was contemporary with the Apoſtle
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93080:21"/>St. <hi>Peter;</hi> or that they would conſiderately ſpeak, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veringly maintain an untruth, imputing a fact to either Apoſtle which he had not done, eſpecially, ſeeing the untruth, on either ſide, might have been confuted by a thouſand witneſſes: wherefore we muſt judge this to be an evident example of a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable apoſtolick inſtitution. I might inſtance in part of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles decree in the 15 chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, of things ſtrangled, and blood; but leaſt I move ſcruples in weak conſciences, which they cannot eaſily be rid of, I will only commend to the conſideration of the judicious the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome ancient writers quoted in the margent.<note place="margin">Auguſt contra Fauſtum l. <hi>32.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Et tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti contra grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos in biblioth. patr. to <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>1308.</hi> et <hi>1318.1319.1320.</hi>
               </note> There be many rites which the Fathers held to be Apoſtolical, which in the times of the ſame Fathers, were in many places altered or neglected; as the three immerſions in baptiſme; the repairing of neighbour Biſhops to the people where a Biſhop was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there to ordain one in the preſence of the people; not to faſt in the dayes of Pentecoſt, and ſome other; which prove that according to the judgment of thoſe Fathers, the Apoſtles, (guided by divine inſpiration) made ſome decrees alterable, and which were upon juſt reaſons accordingly changed or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed: and therefore if it were proved, that the Apoſtles by divine motion were the primary Auctors of Epiſcopacy and not the Church; yet if it cannot appeare to be a conſtitution built upon perpetuall reaſon, and in its nature independing upon variable circumſtances, it may poſſibly be changed by the Church.</p>
            <p>Here it may be demanded by what members of it ſelf did the univerſal Church abrogate the Presbyterian and inſtitute Epiſcopal Government; and what power was taken from the Presbyters by that abrogation? For anſwer to theſe demands, we muſt diſtingniſh between the power given to miniſters, to doe ſome things; as to preach, baptize, ordain Paſtors, excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, abſolve, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſecondly, the free exerciſe of thoſe acts, and thirdly, the regulation of the exerciſe of them, as to the perſons about whom, time when, the place where, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, decency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the regulation belong, 1. The making of laws concerning the due exerciſe of the power, agreeable to the divine laws, and ſecondly the ſuperintendents of the execution, and thirdly the executors of them. As for the power, it doth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93080:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>not appear, that any of that was taken from the Presbyters or their Colledge by the inſtitution of Epiſcopacy, if they were deprived of any part of it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>can.</hi> 13.</note> that muſt be the ordaining of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> ſeems to demonſtrate, that the power of ordaining Paſtors did and doth remain in them, which they did exerciſe by the leave,<note place="margin">Et Synod An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch c. <hi>16.</hi> vide Vaſque. in <hi>3.</hi> p. Diſp. <hi>143.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and in the place of the Biſhop which Could not at his pleaſure give them, but ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the power continuing in them. The words of the Council be theſe (according to the Greek Original and not their vulgar tranſlation) it is not lawful (ſay the Fathers of that Synod) for the Choropiſcopi (Countrey, or Village Biſhops) not for the Presbyters of the City to ordain Presbyters or Deacons, unleſs that be committed to them by the Biſhop (being abſent in another Dioceſs) by his letters. And therefore the Churches decree conſtituting Epiſcopacy, abridged the Presbyters whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dividedly, or conjunctly conſidered, but onely in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their power. Surely it muſt be beleeved, that no ordination would be made by the Apoſtles excelling the ordination which our Saviour celebrated, breathing upon his Apoſtles <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them a comiſsion to teach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with promiſe to be with them unto the worlds end, whereby the Presbyters were virtual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained and comiſſionated astruly as the Biſhops, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received thereby as much power as they in reſpect of the kind and nature; which hinders not, but that the exerciſe of ſome part of it might be taken from many of the perſons ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But ſome perhaps may ſay, that Chriſt in that ordination or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the Apoſtles ſome as elder Brethren, and others as the younger, yet hence it will follow, that the kind and nature of the ordination is the ſame in all, (as the nature of the Father is in all his Sons) and that onely a principallity in the having and exerciſe of it belongs to the Biſhops; which is granted. Others may ſay farther, that Chriſt in ordaining the Apoſtles did vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ordain ſome as the Sons of the Sons of the Apoſtles, and others as their grand-children; if this can be well proved, it will indeed evince, that the power of ordination, as well as the exerciſe of it, is proper to the Biſhops; but until it be made clear, that this was the primary meaning and intention of Chriſt in that Act of ordination, and not an effect onely of a conſequent occaſional
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93080:22"/>providence of the Apoſtles and Churches, it is probable that the power of ordination remaineth ſtill in the presbyters reſtrained in the uſe by the canon of the Churches and Apoſtles. The members of the Church, which made the decree of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy and limited the uſe of the Ecleſiaſtical power, in the pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, were the greater number of the presbyters themſelves which remained in the unity of the myſtical body with the greater part of the people; and the Authors of it by way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and confirmation were the holy Apoſtles. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Presbyters, in the effecting of it, exerciſed the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, Vicary Authority,<note place="margin">Baſil. conſtit. mona. c. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> which they had as being by their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation made the Vicegerents of the bleſſed Mediator Chriſt Jeſus (conſidered only as Mediator) according to his own ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>he that heareth you, heareth me and he that deſpiſeth you deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me,</hi> &amp; the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>we are Emb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſadors for Chriſt and we pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye reconciled to God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> That autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity when it is duely exerciſed ought to be obeyed. And becauſe presbyters may erre in the uſing of it, a ſpirit of diſcerning noxious doctrines and conſtitutions is given to Chriſtians to examine and trie,<note place="margin">Baſ. l. reg. <hi>72.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> with command to reject the evil and receive the good: which good, if the major part refuſe, being by their Paſtors propounded to them,<note place="margin">Aug. de temp. ſerm. <hi>143.</hi>
               </note> they may do it upon their peril, &amp; as they will anſwer it to God; unity and peace interceding and forbidding that no Eccleſiaſtical conſtraint or cenſure proceed againſt the civil higher power, or the major part of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. It is therefore requiſite, that conſtitutions to be made laws in the Church, be, by the leave of the ſupreme magiſtrate, if he be a Chriſtian, propounded to the people, that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being given, the miniſterial authority may make them laws Eccleſiaſtically obliging, if no higher authority hinder. Before theſe Law-makers conſtituted Epiſcopacy, every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Presbyter was to act according to the directions and rules of the Presbyterian Colledge, which was the Church Law-giver, and ſuperintendent of the execution, having the ſupreme dignity under the Mediator, and preheminence in all things properly Eccleſiaſtical. What is ſpoken concerning the Colledge of Presbyters muſt be applied proportionably to the ſeveral bodies of them in the Dioceſan, provincial, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93080:22"/>or univerſal Church. The decree conſtituting Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, took from the Colledge its high dignity and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and conferred it upon one, and ſo divided the exerciſe of the Legiſlative power among the Biſhop and the Colledge, that the one might not duely uſe it without the other. For although the dignity and precedency of the Biſhop may give more weight to his vote, yet is the Vicary authority (which cannot be ſeparated from Presbyters as long as they be Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters) as truly exerciſed in their votes, whether in deciding controverſies of faith, or making of Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it is in the Biſhops vote: Which is manifeſt, as by many teſtimonies of antiquity, ſo by the practiſe of our Engliſh Synods, which are conformable, in the ſubſtance, to the beſt and moſt ancient conſtitution of Councils. The ſuperintendency, which the Colledge had over the execution of all Eccleſiaſtical duties and ordinances, was chiefly in the Biſhop, yet ſo as without his Presbyters he could not regularly hear and determine Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cauſes, as before was ſhewed out of the fourth Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and might be further demonſtrated out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and other ancient writers.</p>
            <p>Every ſuprem civil power on earth, as Gods Vicegerent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</note> is bound to advance, and preſerve the true Religion, ſo far as the light of nature can manifeſt it, or divine revelation doth make it known unto him: ſo that a King, which hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Chriſtian Religion (which alone is the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is obliged to maintain it, and to cauſe that the Chriſtian duties be by all in their ſeveral ſtations and charges duely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; and therefore a Chriſtian King is a law-giver above the Eccleſiaſtical Law-makers; but ſo, that he ought not to hinder the due exerciſe of their legiſlative power, and make laws purely or properly Eccleſiaſtical, without their concurrence in Counſel and conſent: but by his Laws and power, partly to cauſe them to meet for the due exerciſe of their duty, partly to maintain and ſtrengthen their right proceedings in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their office, and laſtly (if their Edicts be coſiſtant with the peace of the common-wealth, and meet for the edification of the Church) to perfect and make them full and complete laws, by putting the hand and ſeal of his higheſt Vicary authority, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93080:23"/>Gods Vicegerent, to the reſolves of the ſubordinate Vicary, authority of the Vicegerents of our bleſſed Mediator, as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator God and man, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. God is a God of order, and hath ordained that this unity and harmony between theſe two authorities ſhould be firmly kept, otherwiſe by a ſupine neglect of duty or by an exorbitant uſurpation on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the unity and peace, both of Kingdome and Church are equally in danger of being broken. The propounding of the true doctrine in deciſion of controverſies, or of conſtitutions of expedient or neceſſary to aedification are acts of religion moſt proper to the Biſhops, and presbyters; the firſt an act of the praedication of the goſpel; the other an act of eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The embracing of the truth and ordinances ſeen to be profitable together with the confirming of them by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and ſanction, or addition (where he ſeeth it needful) of a reward or mulct, is the part of a Chriſtian Prince diſcerning upon due ſearch, the truth and the uſefulneſſe, of the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces propounded unto him; whoſe embracing is his act of ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Chriſt; and confirmation and ſanction, an act of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary authority. To make laws beſtowing civil gifts or privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges on the Church, and ordaining civil puniſhments for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences committed againſt Chriſtian religion and Eccleſiaſtical Canons, and conſtituting Courts for the cognizance of ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the execution of thoſe Laws, is the peculiar and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per work of a Chriſtian King, which he may well doe without the authority of Biſhops and presbyters; but which he may beſt doe with their grave advice and counſel.</p>
            <p>In the unanimous Votes of the Kings Majeſty, the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes of Parliament, and the venerable convocation, all Powers and intereſts are fully ſatisfied, whether in deciſion of controverſies in religion,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>2.</hi> Cor. hom. <hi>18,</hi> &amp;c. Sect. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> or making Eccleſiaſtical Canons, or any the like Eccleſiaſtical matters, becauſe they are the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct Votes of all the concerned.</p>
            <p>Before the civil Magiſtrate became Chriſtian, the Clergy and people according to their ſeverall rights, concurred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally in the elections of Biſhops and Presbyters; and this remained in uſe under many Chriſtian Emperors and Kings, untill for the avoyding of contention and ſchiſmes and many
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93080:23"/>abuſes (which became familiar to popular elections in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſtate of the Church) and for the encouragement of Princes, Nobles and others to erect and endow Churches, it ſeemed good to Kings in their Parliaments, and with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation or Synod of the Biſhops and Clergy, to ordain, that Kings ſhould preſent to the Colledge of Presbyters, meet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be choſen and made Biſhops, and meet Presbyters to the Biſhop for ſuch Churches as they had built and endowed; and that all other perſons ſhould in like manner preſent to the Biſhop a fit perſon for the Church which they had endowed. Patrons did indeed in ſome places put in whom they pleaſed without the Biſhops conſent,<note place="margin">Vide Epiſt. Alexandr. <hi>3.</hi> ad Epiſcopos Angliae.</note> and for ſome time of publick confuſion this was very uſually done in <hi>England;</hi> but this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was no law, as ſome would have it, becauſe it was an unreaſonable cuſtome, and deſtructive to the Church, and therefore always contradicted in all Councils where occaſion was given to mention it.</p>
            <p>All humane laws have their mixture of ſome bad with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good: And certain it is, that our Eccleſiaſtical laws have many imperfections; and their ambiguous halting between the papal Canon-law, (whence their interpretation hath been wont to be fetched) and the laws of the Realm, is not the leaſt; which hath been one of the principal occaſions of ſome act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which made the Clergy much abhorred by many, and brought infinite calamities upon the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical ſtate.</p>
            <p>The ancient pure Epiſcopal government is much changed, and the beginning of its change was not of late dayes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</note> for in the fourth Century the Biſhops and Presbyters began to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Arch-presbyters and Arch-deacons to ſome part of the exerciſe of the Eccleſiaſtical government.<note place="margin">Optat. adverſ. Parmenian. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> The firſt Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon we read of was <hi>Caecilianus,</hi> who reproved <hi>Lucilla</hi> a rich and proud woman, which being thereat vexed, became after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a zealous promotrix of the Schiſm of the Donatiſts. The firſt Arch-presbyter,<note place="margin">Greg. Nazianz. in land. Baſil. crat.</note> that I can remember to be mentioned by the ancients, was <hi>Baſile;</hi> who being made Biſhop, offered that honour to his old friend <hi>Gregory,</hi> after the Biſhop of <hi>Nazianzum.</hi> But theſe were at that time but in ſome Churches,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93080:24"/>and acted onely in place of the Biſhops and Presbyters and at their pleaſure; whereas their power in time increaſed, and after ſome hundreds of years, the Canons gave them an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary juriſdiction, erected their Courts, added new names of Eccleſiaſtical judges, as Deans, Chancellors, Commiſſaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and filled them with numerous attendants, which were moſtly to live by the ſins of the people. If theſe had been Officers onely of the civil magiſtrate, to execute the power which is proper to him over all perſons, and in all cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, the Church could not in reaſon have been charged with their miſcariages: but becauſe they exerciſed with the former, acts of the power proper to Biſhops and Presbyters, and in which the civil magiſtrate had onely a ſuperintendency over them, all their miſdoings were aſcribed to the Biſhops and the Clergy: their Courts heard the cauſes of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, adjudg'd a perſon to excommunication, and cauſed a Presbyter, no judge in the cauſe, to excommunicate the party: whereas Chriſt by his Apoſtles made them judges in his place as well to hear the cauſes of the ſpiritual cenſures, as to execute the ſame by the ſentence of excommunication. The ſpiritual cenſures are ſpiritual remedies, and the Paſtors of the Church, are under Chriſt the Phyſicians; how then can it be congruous, to imploy one that is no Phyſician to ſearch and take knowledge of the diſeaſes of the Soul, and leave or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the application of the remedies to the Phyſicians? in the hearing of the cauſes of ſpiritual cenſures, paſtoral acts are to be exerciſed, as of teaching, of redargution of ſin, and conviction, which prepare the offendor for the due and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable receiving of the ſpiritual Phyſick; which acts are all wanting where a perſon that is no Paſtor condemneth a ſinner to be excommunicated by a Paſtor.</p>
            <p>There is another miſchief that accompanies the mixture in one and the ſame perſon of the exerciſe of acts purely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial and acts proper to the civil magiſtrate in ſpiritual cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (as it is in Arch-deacons and the like) that is, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of paenance (as to take ſo much money, a Cow, a Horſe, and the like, as it hath been uſed) be it in pretence of giving it to the poor, where ſuſpenſion or excommunication was by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93080:24"/>the Apoſtolical ordinances to have been exerciſed. If the power proper to the miniſters, &amp; the power proper to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate were in diſtinct perſons, this too frequent abuſe would be well avoyded; For the ſole ſpiritual power is not to medle with body or purſe: Cudgelling, whipping, impriſoning fining ſcandalous ſinners were not at all in uſe before the times of Chriſtian Emperours. And as to the redemption of the wholeſome ſeverities, which the paenitents were enjoyned willingly to exerciſe upon themſelves, it was not uſed until about the end of the fift Century.</p>
            <p>I might mention other miſchiefs, as the intollerable abuſe of excommunication for very ſmall offences (of old con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the Canons of the Church) under pretence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy, or the like: But I am weary of raking in this puddle,<note place="margin">Concil. Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; Leo. Epiſt. <hi>87.</hi>
               </note> where the many dependences upon thoſe Courts ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire exorbitances, that every one might have a tolerable livelyhood. If the excreſcencies, which the corruptions of the times made to adhere to the primitive Epiſcopacy, were cut off, and the ſpiritual juriſdiction reſtored to the Biſhop and Presbyters, it is not to be doubted,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>(i.e. mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus baptizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. hom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but that our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren who diſlike the Epiſcopacy in its preſent conſtitution, and the more, becauſe they took an oath (whether well or ill I let go) to endevour the abrogation of it, would be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with the Apoſtolical Epiſcopacy, where one was ordained for the union &amp; ſtrengthening of the juriſdiction of Presbyters: for the defence of which Epiſcopacy, they had taken a former oath in the ſolemn Proteſtation, which, as taken lawfully and in lawful things, maketh all contrary oaths unlawful to be after either taken or kept.</p>
            <p>Although the Apoſtles ordained no governing Elders beſides the Biſhop and preaching Elders, yet the primitive Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will well bear, that ſome lay Elders be joyned to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, and in every pariſh, (where fit perſons may be had,) to help the Biſhop and Presbyters in the inſpection of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in the inſtruction of the ignorant, in brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and teproofs, and in giving notice to the Biſhops and Presbyters of the ſcandalous offences, to be proceeded againſt in an Eccleſiaſtical order, and alſo to repreſent the people and vote for them; where their conſent is requiſite.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93080:25"/>
            <p>Here I deſire it may be noted, that when I ſpake of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters which were the Senate of the ancient Biſhops,<note place="margin">Conc. Neocae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. cum Ep. <hi>7.</hi> Zachariae papae ad Bonifac. c. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>15.</hi> Et Concil. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſ. an. <hi>845.</hi> c. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not all and every one ſubject unto the Biſhop, but the more ancient, grave, pious, learned, diſcreet and moderate of them; for ſuch were the City Presbyters in the old times which alone uſually and moſtly were the Biſhops aſſeſſors in the ſpiritual judicature, and which therefore in ſome places and ſpecially in <hi>Rome</hi> obtained the name of Cardinal Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters.</p>
            <p>Some diſlike the civil honour wherewith godly Kings have dignified our reverend Prelates:<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> truely, if the taking of it had made them leſs able to fulfil the office of preaching the Goſpel, or did widen the diſtance between them and the Presbyters, or made them leſs acceſſible by or condeſcending to their flock, or ecclipſed the veneration due to their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, or involved them in civil affaires, which all the ancient Canons forbid, the addition of that honour were not to be liked: but it is evident enough to the eye of every impartial judgement, and the lives of many moſt holy Biſhops have made it good, that if any of theſe evils happen'd from the receiving of that dignity, as too often hath been ſeen, it proceeded from the evil of the perſon, and not from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent honour, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s conferred upon them by pious Princes out of their love to Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and his Ambaſſadors, the better to preſerve them from the contempt of the wicked, (who regard no goodneſs beſides the civil and worldly) and to enable the better to maintain the great intereſt which in civil things belongs to the Eccleſiaſtical eſtate, and that the great Council of a Chriſtian Kingdom ſhould not ſit without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt an honourable place and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge among them, that in them Chriſt might be ſeen to be the more preſent, and their ready ſpiritual Council might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſome proceedings not well agreeing with the intereſt of religion and the laws of Chriſt, which without them might more eaſily happen. But what was done in a heat, may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done in a milder temper. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> who was born within very few years after the deceaſe of the Apoſtles ſaith, that the Church nouriſhed ſuch presbyters, of whom the Prophet ſaith,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93080:25"/>I will give thy Princes in peace and thy Biſhops in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where this ancient Father doth ſhew that Biſhops be princes. And ſo doth <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the place, the prophet (ſaith he) calleth the future princes of the Church Biſhops.<note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>60.17.</hi> Secund. <hi>70.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret.</note> It is then very congruous that the Chriſtian Kings ſet over theſe Eccleſiaſtical princes, and by their miniſtery made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the caeleſtial dignities, ſhould in a certain way of retribution dignifie them with ſome eminent degree of civil honour, which cannot be well ſupported without ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable revenue.</p>
            <p>The Holy Scripture tells us, that it is a more bleſſed thing to give, then to receive: Surely God would have every of the presbyters of the Church enabled for that bleſſed work of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, over and above a convenient maintenance for Wife and Children, which the Apoſtle ſuppoſeth to be in their families, for whom they are bound to provide, or in the judgment of the ſame Apoſtle to be deemed to have denied the faith, and to be worſe then infidels. And if every Presbyter ought to be thus provided for (if poſſible) then the elder Brethren ſhould have a double portion, beſides the proportion which their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil dignity doth require; and where any of the reſt are indued with more excellent miniſterial gifts, it's very convenient they ſhould have a larger meaſure of the matter and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments requiſite for the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l exerciſe of their more excelling vertues. What the revenue of the reverend Biſhops is, I do not know, but I have good reaſons to aſſure me that it is not exceſſive, at which any would grudg or envy, except the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious truckers, which would have the reverend Clergy live upon their leavings and ſcraps. Certain it is that the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of many hundreds of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>sbyters is ſo ſmall that they can ſcarſe feed and cloath their Families, ſo that when they die, many Hoſpitals might be filled with their poor Wives and Children. And if no better proviſion be made for the poor Cures and Vicarages, it were an eminent work of charity to erect and endow Hoſpitals proper to poor Miniſters Wives and Children. This ſtarving of Chriſts Ambaſſadours is the ſhame and great ſin of the Kingdome: But now it is the hope and expectation of all good men, that his ſacred Majeſty and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93080:26"/>moſt honourable houſes of parliament will provide a remedy for this miſerable diſeaſe of the Church, for it's onely an act of parliament that can ſurely, ſweetly, and fully cure it.</p>
            <p>There be not a few who complain againſt the canonical oath:<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> concerning which I can find no mention until about the year 813. wherein the Fathers of the ſecond Council of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon</hi> ſay, it is ſpoken of certain of our brethren that they compel them whom they are to ordain to ſwear that they will do nothing againſt the Canons, and that they will be obedient to the Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which oath becauſe it is dangerous; we do all with one conſent ordain, that it be prohibited. A Canon of a Council celebrated <hi>an.</hi> 1355, comes to my mind, which ſaith, leſt the faithful (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the divine piety was mercifully pleaſed to put under a light burthen and a ſweet yoke) ſhould be burthened with the weight of ſin, by reaſon of their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions againſt the Canons; we ordain that the provincial conſtitutions of our predeceſſors, and thoſe which ſhall be hereafter made, oblige not the trangreſſors to ſin <hi>(ad culpam)</hi> but onely to puniſhment <hi>(ad paenam.)</hi> Whether the modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Synods be worthy of imitation, I leave to others to judge.</p>
            <p>Many have entertained a great fear,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> which hath alienated their minds from all Epiſcopacy; namely, that an innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company of unneceſſary and burthenſome ceremonies be inſeparable concomitants of Epiſcopal government. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the fear is not vain and without ground, if we reſpect the degenerated Epiſcopacy, as it is, if we regard the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which hath and will be contented with very few, if need be. Witneſs <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, who ſaith, that it was the cuſtome of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Greg. Epiſt. l. T. Ep. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> to conſecrate the Euchariſt, uſing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lords prayer; with him agrees <hi>Walifridus Strabus;</hi> it is the relation of our Anceſtors (ſaith he) that the Maſs was wont to be made in the firſt times as now in the Good Friday,<note place="margin">De rebus Eccl. c. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> after the Lords Prayer, and the commemoration of Chriſts paſſion, as himſelf hath taught us, the communion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of our Lord was given to all that were prepared. About forty years after the death of St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> relates,<note place="margin">In Apolog. ad Auton.</note> that when the people of the City and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93080:26"/>Countrey adjacent met together on the Lords day, the Reader read out of the Apoſtles and Prophets, and then the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent made a Sermon upon the Scripture then read; which ended, all ſtood up to prayer; which done they kiſſed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: then bread and wine and water were offered to the Preſident; which he having received prayed again, and gave thanks as he was able; which ended, the people ſaid, <hi>amen.</hi> Then the Deacons gave the conſecrated bread &amp; wine and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to every one preſent to receive, and they carried the ſame to the abſent. Here we have the ſubſtance of the ancient Liturgy of the Church in uſe at that time, ſhort and ſweet: Where the Lords prayer was not alone uſed in the conſecration, as in the Apoſtles time, but alſo the Biſhops prayer, whereof the words [as he was able] may imply, either that he prayed as well as his memory would ſerve him to utter a premeditated prayer without book, or that he prayed as devoutly as he could, which is the beſt conſtruction of them. So that hence it may not appear whether it was a read, or a premeditated and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially delivered prayer. The ſame old author ſaith concerning Baptiſm; as many as believe thoſe things to be true which have been told and taught them by us, and promiſe to live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, are inſtructed to pray faſting for the pardon of their ſins, we faſting and praying with them; and then they are by us brought to the water and regenerated, as we our ſelves were, in the name of the Father and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Holy Ghoſt, being waſhed in the water: Then we bring them to the Brethren who are met together making common prayers for themſelves, the baptized, and all other where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are to note that he mentions a <hi>Reader,</hi> which whether he were a Presbyter or a Deacon, or a diſtinct degree inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Church, cannot be gathered from his writings which are now extant. In the end of the ſecond Century the Reader appears to be a diſtinct degree; the ordinations of Haereticks (ſaith <hi>Tertull.</hi>) are raſh, light, unconſtant, therefore one is with them to day a Biſhop, and another to morrow,<note place="margin">De praeſcript. haeret. c. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> he is to day a Deacon which ſhall be the next day a Reader, he is to day a presbyter which is the next day a Laick. And it is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93080:27"/>to be ſeen in <hi>Cyprian</hi> about the year 250,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 22.</note> that he ordained <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius</hi> and <hi>Saturus</hi> Readers in his Church, and <hi>Optatus</hi> a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon. At the ſame time <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (writing to <hi>Fabius</hi>) ſaith,<note place="margin">Apud Euſeb. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> that in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> there were of Presbyters forty ſix, of Deacons ſeven, of ſub-deacons ſeven, of Acolythes 42, of Exorciſts, Readers, and Porters 52, of Widows and Poor above 1500, all which the Church fed.</p>
            <p>Here we find Exorciſts and Readers (both which were in <hi>Juſtin Martyrs</hi> time about the year 150) to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Clergy of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Reader diſtinguiſhed from the Presbyter and Deacons. After this, about the year 400, the diſtinct ordinations of Biſhops, of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, of Deacons, of Sub-deacons, of Acolythes, of Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſts, or Readers, and of Porters or Dore-keepers, and of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, are ſet down in the fourth Council of <hi>Carthage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conc. Carth. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> It muſt not be imagined that any of theſe, beſides a Presbyter and Dore-keeper, was in every Parochial Church, but only in the Cathedral or mother Church of the Dioceſs, and in ſome ſuch parochial Churches as were able to maintain a greater or leſſer number of them. And therefore it ſeems hard to lay upon one miniſter in the pariſh Church the burthen of all the offices, to be born by himſelf alone, which in the Cathedral were executed by many. As to read every Lords day all the ſervice firſt and ſecond, being a thing above the ſtrength of moſt, if the Sermon be not omitted; as the Biſhops and Presbyters bordering upon the times of the Apoſtles, with the peoples conſent, committed the office of reading the holy Scriptures in the Churches to men of an inferior ordination, ſo their ſucceſſors ſhortly after committed the office of teaching the Catechumens to the like perſons, but more learned and apt to teach. Both theſe (as alſo ſome others) were ſeparated from the Laicks and deſtinated for the Presbytery: They were the Biſhops and Presbyters Scholars, bred up by them for the high and ſacred miniſtery, and advanced thereto, if they became capable, and the Church had need of them. So that Readers and Catechiſers were incomplete preachers of the Goſpel, until by the higher and divine ordination Chriſt breathed upon them, giving them the Holy Ghoſt, which made them
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93080:27"/>complete preachers; who do not perform a complete act of preaching, unleſs with the publiſhing of the text, wherein the Readers help them; they alſo publiſh an expoſition and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation thereupon; as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> did, and the ſucceeding ancient Fathers; who grounded their Homilies, or Sermons upon a portion of the Scriptures then read before them. One or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God is not to be made to thruſt another out of the Church, but reading and prayers, and preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to be ſo proportioned to the time appointed for them, and the ſtrength of them that officiate, that no neceſſity, that may be prevented, may compel to the omiſſion of any divine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance that ought to be performed. In the ſixt Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (at which time much corruption was crept into the Churches) the Fathers preſent in it commanded, that the Biſhops and Presbyters ſhould dayly preach,<note place="margin">Gan. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially on the Lords day. It is commanded by another Council, that if a Presbyter cannot preach by reaſon of ſickneſs,<note place="margin">Conc. Vaſenſ. Can. <hi>4.</hi> ſub Leone. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that a homily or ſermon of one of the ancient Fathers be read by the Deacon. In another Council, its thus decreed; that if the Biſhop be not at home, or is infirm, or is not able for ſome other cauſe, yet never let on the Lords days or Feſtivals any want to be of one which may preach the Word of God, ſo as the vulgar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may underſtand.<note place="margin">Concil. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntiac. c. <hi>25.</hi> circa an. <hi>813.</hi>
               </note> The Primitive Biſhops were preaching Biſhops, and uſually preached every Lords day (as we ſee in <hi>Juſtine Martyr,</hi>) and in Feſtival days in the principal faſting days in <hi>Lent,</hi> as we find in <hi>Ambroſe, Chryſoſt. Auguſtine</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But I muſt return to ſpeak of the Ceremonies of the Church. The Ceremony of ſtanding and not kneeling in prayer on the Lords days, and the days between <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> was in uſe in the Apoſtles days, and inſtituted by them;<note place="margin">Apud anthorem Chriſtian. reſp. reſp. <hi>115.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the hearer of <hi>Polycarpus</hi> Auditor of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>John</hi> doth teſtifie. In the time of <hi>Tertullian</hi> about the year 200, many other Ceremonies are mentioned by him, (which we find not in any approved Author before him ſpoken of) and are affirmed by him to deſcend from the Apoſtles; as the ſigning of the forehead of the baptized with the ſign of the Croſs, beſides,<note place="margin">Tertull. de co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona militis c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the uſual ſigning with the ſame ſign upon ſundry occaſions, the taſting after Baptiſm of milk and honey, the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93080:28"/>uſe of having Suerties for Infants to be baptized,<note place="margin">De Bapt. c. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of the baptiſed with oyl, Offering for the faithful deceaſed, which was thus: the friends of the deceaſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered bread and wine in their behalf for the uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper, and the Prieſt by faith in prayer, in the celebration of the Euchariſt, preſented to God the Father the ſacrifice of Chriſt once offered by him, and which was in ſome manner preſent in the Sacrament, beſeeching him for that moſt holy and perfect ſacrifice ſake to take away the remainder of ſin from the ſoul departed (which was not taken away in this life) both as to the guilt and inhaerency of it, and to grant to the ſoul the promiſed preſent bleſſed reſt, and in the day of judgment, to make the perſon partaker of the publick juſtification and poſſeſſion of full faelicity. Before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Lords Supper they kiſſed one another with the holy kiſs, the ſign of true love and peace; which we are ſure was uſed in the Apoſtles dayes, and ſeems to argue ſtrongly for the uſe of <hi>ſignificant</hi> Ceremonies. The Eaſter and Pentecoſt were the ſet and ſolemn times of the adminiſtration of the Sacrament of Baptiſm.<note place="margin">de bapt. c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> I need not ſpeak of Confirmation, of the obſervation of the Feaſts of Eaſter and Pentecoſt, of the faſt in the days of our Saviour's death and burial, of the leſs perfect and voluntary faſts of <hi>Friday</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. de jejun. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> which be in part before touched; for my purpoſe is not to make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act collection of the ancient rites, but of ſuch as may give ſome light to ſee, whence thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Ceremonies, which have been and partly are uſed in our Church, took their beginnings.</p>
            <p>As concerning the geſture of the body uſed in the prayers of the Church,<note place="margin">de Orat. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> it was kneeling or ſtanding; this laſt on the Lords dayes,<note place="margin">Tertul. l. <hi>2.</hi> ad uxor. c. <hi>9.</hi> de Monogam. <hi>6.10</hi>
               </note> and in all the Pentecoſt: For as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, it is a moſt irreligious fact to pray to God ſitting before him, unleſs we upbraid Him that prayer hath wearied us.</p>
            <p>Concerning Matrimony;<note place="margin">De Veland. Virg. c. <hi>11.</hi> de pudicitia. c. <hi>9.</hi> Ambroſ. Ep. <hi>70.</hi> Nazianz. Epiſt. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time, they defired of the Biſhops, presbyters, Deacons and Widows, leave to marry; they were married by a Biſhop or presbyter, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man uſed a Vaile, they joyned their right hands, kiſſed; and <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth alſo ſeem to intimate the uſe of a ring, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93080:28"/>it was in uſe in <hi>Iſidors</hi> time and before:<note place="margin">Iſidor. de Eccl. offic. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> the Bridegroom (ſaith he) gave a Ring to the Bride, which was put upon her fourth Finger.</p>
            <p>We may gather from <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De bapt. c. <hi>9.</hi> Apolog. conta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent. c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> that the Lords prayer was commonly uſed in the publick prayers of the Church; for he calls it the legitime and ordinary prayer, which (ſaith he) being laid as a foundation, we may build upon it the petitions which our particular caſes require. He ſhews, that our private prayers, wherein we expreſs to God our particular wants and deſires, muſt not be loud, not altogether ſet formes, but promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, without ſuch monitor, by our own hearts, which alone can tell us our particular neceſſities. When we pray (ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi>) let the Father acknowledge the words of his Son:<note place="margin">Cypr. de orat. Dom.</note> And we do (ſaith he) the more effectually obtain what we ask in Chriſts name, if we ask uſing his own prayer.<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>42.</hi> ex <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> The Lords prayer (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is dayly ſaid at the Altar of God in his Church. The fourth Council of <hi>Tolet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> called it a Quotidian, a dayly prayer, and commanded it to be ſaid by the Clergy, not onely on the Lords days, but every day both in the publick and private duty. Concerning prayer,<note place="margin">de orat. dom.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath theſe remarkable words; when we ſtand to prayer (ſaith he) our mind muſt be onely upon that it prayeth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prieſt, premiſing a preface before the prayer, prepares the minds of the Brethren; ſaying, Lift up your hearts; that the people anſwering, We have unto the Lord, may be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed they ought to think on no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing but the Lord: By which words we learn two things; Firſt, that in <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s time (which was 250 years after our Saviour's birth) ſet forms of publick prayers were uſed in the Churches. Secondly, that the people had other anſwers beſides [Amen] to make to the miniſter in the ſolemn prayers of the Church.<note place="margin">De bono per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverantiae. c. <hi>13.</hi> &amp; de Spir. &amp; lit. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth what followeth thoſe words of the publick prayers mentioned by <hi>Cyprian;</hi> the Prieſt ſaid (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) let us give thanks to our Lord God, to which the people an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, it is meet and right ſo to do; and then the Prieſt went no ſaying, it is very meet, right, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of Authors now extant, who flouriſhed in the three firſt Centuties, no more (that I can remember) concerning
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93080:29"/>the divine ſervice of the Church and the Ceremonies, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to our purpoſe, is mentioned, then what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready touched. But the holy writers of the fourth Century and downward do affirm, both that many other rites have been uſed in the three firſt Centuries, whereof ſome were inſtituted by the Apoſtles (as they write) others by ſome Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that many more were added in the fourth Century. One reaſon why the Ceremonies increaſed in the fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury may be this; becauſe then the Church more flouriſhed in proſperity, then any time before, and it might be thought convenient that the external glory of the Church ſhould be proportioned to the glory of the Empite now made Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The uſe of ſinging Pſalmes and Hymnes in the Churches,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> may (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) be defended out of Scripture, ſeeing of this we have ſo profitable inſtructions, examples and precepts of Chriſt and his Apoſtles: But the manner of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was various.<note place="margin">l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> relateth that <hi>Ignatius,</hi> having in a viſion ſeen Angels ſinging Hymnes Anthemewiſe unto the praiſe of the Holy Trinity, delivered that manner of ſinging Pſalmes unto his own Church in <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally received thence by the Greek Churches, and then by the Latines and <hi>Weſt,</hi> firſt by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the fourth Century, and after by the reſt of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Biſhops. The Rubrick in our Common-prayer Book before <hi>Te Deum laudamus</hi> (we praiſe thee O God) hath theſe words; that the people may the better hear, in ſuch places where they do ſing, there ſhall the Leſſons be ſung in a plain tune after the manner of diſtinct reading, and likewiſe the Epiſtle and Goſpel. This Rubrick puts me in mind of a place in St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s Confeſſions,<note place="margin">l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> where he ſaith, that it was often told him, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> made the reader of the Pſalm to ſound with ſo mean bending or turning of the Voyce, that he might be nearer a pronouncer then a ſinger:<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> And in another place he ſaith; when the Brethren are met in the Church, when is it not time of ſinging holy ſongs, unleſs it be the time of reading, or preaching, or of prayer? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which words it ſeemeth that the Chapters, Epiſtle and Goſpel were not ſung in thoſe dayes. And in truth any manner of ſinging them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93080:29"/>ſeemeth incongruous. The Fathers uſe to reprove the abuſes which were too often found in ſinging Pſalms in the Churches, eſpecially, that they were many times more pleaſed with the ſweetneſs of the voyce then the divine matter, or when onely a few of the Church did ſing, that they ſo ſung that few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood what they ſung.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Epheſ. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Let the ſervant of the Lord (ſaith <hi>Hierome</hi>) ſo ſing that the words which he reads may more pleaſe then the voyce of him ſinging. It is no perfect ſinging nor pleaſing to God, when mens hearts do not ſing unto the Lord as well as their voyces. I will not ſpeak of ſinging with Organs in the Churches (not that I think that God refuſeth to be heartily praiſed in and with the uſe of them, but) becauſe they were not brought into the Churches until much later times.</p>
            <p>The Doxology, Glory be to the Father, to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt, for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is by St. <hi>Baſile</hi> proved to be uſed from the Apoſtles times, both out of <hi>Clemens, Rom. Irenaeus, Orig. Gregor. Thaumaturg. Dionyſius Rom. Dionyſius Alex.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Baſil. de Sp. S. c. <hi>29.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ibid.</note> and the Evening-candle light thankſgiving which had been uſed time out of mind of man, wherein they ſaid, We praiſe the Father, and the Son, and the holy Spirit of God. But this Doxology with the addition, as it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was firſt<note n="a" place="margin">Epiſt. Hier. ad Damaſum. Conc. Vaſenſ. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> ordained to be ſaid in the Divine Service of the Church after the Pſalms, by <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> about the year of our Lord 370. He firſt commanded<note n="b" place="margin">Greg. l. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>63.</hi> &amp; inter Ep. Hier. Aug. de temp. ſerm. <hi>151.</hi> de can. obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. <hi>23.</hi> Gregor. l. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>63.</hi> Conc. Vaſenſ. c. <hi>5.</hi> Radulfſ Vigreſ. de can. obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. praepoſit. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alleluia</hi> to be uſed in the Roman Church, following therein the Liturgie of the <hi>Hieroſolymitane</hi> and Greek Churches. <hi>Kyrie eleiſon</hi> and <hi>Chriſte eleiſon,</hi> Lord have mercy and Chriſt have mercy often repeated were in imitation of ſome greek Liturgies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Romane Divine Service-book by the authority of Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> (about the year 330) ſaith <hi>Radulphus Tugr</hi> which many years after were omitted, and at laſt reſtored by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great.</p>
            <p>The collection of the Epiſties and Goſpels for the whole year into the form like that in preſent uſe is attributed to <hi>Hierom,</hi> and by Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> commanded to be read in the Churches.</p>
            <p>The Symbole or Creed compoſed in the firſt Council of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93080:30"/>
               <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was by the ſame Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> ordained to be ſaid or ſung after the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Rupert. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> Strab. c. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> It was received into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service in <hi>Spain,</hi> by the command of the third Syno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Tolet.</hi> The reaſons brought to prove the Apoſtles or the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Creed to have been ſaid in the Liturgies of the fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury or before are of ſmall weight, and therefore I omit them. How <hi>Damaſus</hi> can truely be ſaid to have enjoyned the ſinging or ſaying of the Creed, and yet that it was not ſung at <hi>Rome,</hi> until about the year 1014 is eaſily anſwered, if we conceive his command to be directed unto all other Churches ſubject unto him,<note place="margin">Berno de offic. myſſae c. <hi>1.</hi> Vide Conc. tolet. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> excepting <hi>Rome,</hi> for that ſpecial reaſon which <hi>Berno</hi> relates.</p>
            <p>Biſhops, Presbyters, and Deacons, in the time of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">Hierom. l. <hi>1.</hi> dial. contra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. Chryſoſt. in Matt. hom. <hi>83.</hi> Conc. Carthag. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>41.</hi> Et vide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſs. Leonis <hi>3.</hi> ad miſſos ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli M. ſub Conc. aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granenſ</note>, uſed the white garment, which we call the Surplice; whether it was in uſe before the fourth Century is not related by any approved author living in thoſe times. Prayers compoſed after the manner of our Litany are to be ſeen in the Liturgies of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Baſile.</hi> In their time,<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſ. in Ep. ad Eph. hom. <hi>14,</hi> &amp; <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> glory be to God on high, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and<note n="†" place="margin">Idem in Epiſt. ad Coloſſ. hom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Sabboth, were wont to be ſaid in the Divine Service. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, that the Biſhop was wont often in the time of the publik worſhip of God, to ſay to the people,<note n="*" place="margin">in <hi>2</hi> Cor. hom. <hi>18.</hi> &amp; in Ep. ad Coloſſ. hom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Peace be unto you, and that the people anſwered, And with thy ſpirit. The ſame author relating how the people did in another part of the Service anſwer the miniſter; ſaying, Let us give thanks to our Lord God, it is meet and right (ſay the people) ſo to do, addeth,<note n="†" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>2</hi> Cor. hom. <hi>18.</hi> in <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. ad Corinth, hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> why ſhould any marvel that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould (thus in the publick prayers) ſpeak with the Prieſt, ſeeing they ſend up unto Heaven with the Cherubims and Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial powers thoſe holy Hymnes? one reaſon of this is in the ſame place intimated by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> which is, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt unto the people, that the prayers of the Church are not proper to the miniſter, but theirs alſo by joyning with him in them; which is more fully teſtified by their proper prola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome part of them, then onely by their preſence and ſaying Amen. Another reaſon may be the ſame which the ſame Father giveth, of the Deacons exciting the people ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Let us pray, and let us pray more fervently, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93080:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>is, becauſe the Soul is wont to ſlumber in a long prayer. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fathers of the Council of <hi>Bracar</hi> require the Biſhop or Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>yter to ſalute the people in due place in the Divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; ſaying, the Lord be with you; to which the people ſhould anſwer, and with thy Spirit: which ceremony (ſaith the Council) all the <hi>Eaſt</hi> retained as delivered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. The Song of the three Children was generally received into the Liturgies of the Churches in this fourth Century.<note place="margin">Conc. toletam. Ep. c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> It is a tradition that the Hymne <hi>Te Deum landamus, &amp;c.</hi> (We praiſe thee O God We acknowledge thee to be the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) was comdoſed by <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and ſung by <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> after his Baptiſm. <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned all to ſtand at the reading of the Goſpel; after which followed the cuſtome of ſtanding at the reading of the Creed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hierome</hi> writing againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilantius</hi> affirmeth, that in all the Churches of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> when the Goſpel was to be read, candles were lighted the ſun ſhining; not ſurely to drive away darkneſs, but for a ſign of gladneſs.</p>
            <p>In the time of theſe laſt named Doctors, the Feaſts of Saints were more in number, and celebrated with more ſolemnity then in former times. Therein the Feaſt of our Saviours Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity was generally obſerved, and in the ancient Fathers ſenſe, ſaid to be inſtituted by the Apoſtles; whereas no approved Author of the former Centuries make mention of it. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> in a ſermon of his preached by him not long before the year 400, affirmeth,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ſerm. in natalem.</note> that Feaſt not to have come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Churches among which he lived, but ten within years before the preaching of that Sermon.<note place="margin">Tert. de idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria. c. <hi>14.</hi> Vide Georgium in locum &amp; alios.</note> And many Learned men collect from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that in his time no other Feaſts were commanded to be celebrated in the Churches (that he knew of) ſave onely the Lords day, Eaſter and Pentecoſt.</p>
            <p>I ſay not this out of any diſlike of this holy Feaſt,<note place="margin">Ubi multorum ſtrages jacet ſubtrahendum eſt aliquid ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veritati, ut ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur amplius charitati, vide conc. Rom. <hi>3.</hi> an. <hi>1099.</hi>
               </note> or any other, which we receive from thoſe ancient times, (which without the adherent abuſes, I do heartily wiſh to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated with due ſolemnity) but by this example to ſhew, that every thing had not a beginning in the Apoſtles time, which is affirmed to be thence derived and deſcended by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of ſome Fathers, who were both in this matter and other
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93080:31"/>things deceived by the counterfeited Canons and conſtitutions and other writings bearing the names of the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> or <hi>Dionyſius Areopag.</hi> whereof none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re written before the year 300, yet being not well examined were received as genuine by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and ſome other old Doctors of the Church.</p>
            <p>We read in this fourth Century of divers conſecrations and benedictions which we do not read to be uſed in the former times,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16.</note> as of conſecrated Churches, Altars, Paſchal. Wax-candles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and we find therein more regard and honour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to<note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Epiſt. ad Rom. hom. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> relicks of Saints, to the ſign of the Croſs, to the<note n="b" place="margin">Nazianz in laudem Gorgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae &amp; in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Baſilii.</note> Altar or Communion Table, the Bible, and the<note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Eph. hom. 3. In Epiſt. ad Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox. &amp; in apoleg. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Veſſels uſed in the Divine Service and the like, then we can ſee to be given them in former ages; yet piouſly without paſſing the bounds which in thoſe things Chriſtian religion had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, excepting perhaps in ſome particulars which humane frailty might extort from them. Willingly to break the holy Communion Cup, who can ſay but that it is a very great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence? it was (as it was ſaid in <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) to do impiouſly againſt Chriſt, to commit a ſin then which none was greater.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Careleſſeneſs of theſe times in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">Auguſt. hom. <hi>26.</hi> ex <hi>50.</hi> Et Cyrill. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. Myſtagog. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> the faying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is worthy of obſervation: with what care or ſolicitude (ſaith he) do we obſerve, when the body of Chriſt is miniſtred unto us that nothing of it fall to the ground from our hands. It is likely that <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpake before him to the ſame purpoſe: we take it heavily (ſaith he) that any of our Cup or Bread fall to the ground. <hi>Gregory Nazianz.</hi> (treating of the Birth of our bleſſed Saviour) ſaith, Adore the Manger (wherein he was laid.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nazianz. orat. in Chriſti nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem. Hieron. ad Marcellam ut commigret Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſ. idem in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph. Paulae.</note>) The croſs and the ſign were had in no leſs honour: Without the ſign of the Croſs (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) neither Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, nor Confirmation, nor the Lords Supper can be rightly (as to the cuſtomes and Canons of the Church in thoſe times) performed. The Croſs was kiſſed, people fell down before it,<note n="d" place="margin">Paulinus l. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; Chryſoſt. in act. hom. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> adored it: yet <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith of <hi>Helene</hi> the mother of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, that ſhe found the title (of the Croſs) and adored the King (Chriſt) ſurely not the wood; that is the errour of the Gentiles. <hi>Minutius</hi> long before <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93080:31"/>in the name of all Chriſtians, we do not worſhip the Croſs.</p>
            <p>We ſee then, that in thoſe days the Croſs was adored by Chriſtians, and yet that it was not adored by them: It was adored by an Eccleſiaſtical adoration, which was wont to be exhibited to things or perſons accounted excellent, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome dignity and notable uſefulneſs, in being occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, cauſes or inſtruments of ſome very ſingular benefit; it was not adored by an adoration proper to God,<note place="margin">Aug contra Fauſtum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. l. <hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> Super Geneſ. quoeſt. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> nor was it made either improperly or analogically or by accident par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker thereof. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> mentioning <hi>Abrahams</hi> adoring the Ancients of the people of the Land where he ſojourned, ſaith, that therein he did not tranſgreſs Gods command; who did onely forbid men to ſerve the creature with the ſervice and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration called <hi>Latreia.</hi> So <hi>Auguſtine. Latreia</hi> is when the Divine excellencies are the objects of the adoration, and the outward acts of adoration, are ſymboles of the ſubmiſſion of the heart to them. The ancient Fathers did not of their own heads make a creature to ſupply the place of any Divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (as men do, and may make a fellow-creature to ſupply the place of another, and perform ſuch acts of veneration to it as are due to the perſon repreſented, ſuch be the ſtatues of Emperors, and perhaps images and relicks of friends and benefactors) Nor did the Fathers offer ſo to couple any creature unto the Divine perſon of our Saviour to partake in ſome ſort of his adoration, as his apparel, when he lived on earth, was by conjunction with his body made neer to his perſon, even, (as many judge) to an accidental participation of his Divine adoration. It cannot be proved that it was the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church in thoſe times, to exhibite the external acts of divine adoration unto God, in, by, or through any created thing as co-ſubjects or co-objects of them: in all which caſes the inward adoration proper to God is in ſome ſort rendred to the co-adored creature. The intention of thoſe holy men was to adore the croſs onely with an eccleſiaſtical adoration, and ſo adore it for the ſake of Chriſt, and for the benefits ſake redounding from the croſs of Chriſt. They ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red its excellency,<note place="margin">Concil. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinop. quinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſext, Can. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note> which conſiſted in being an inſtrument of the meritorious triumph of Chriſt, and in adoring, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93080:32"/>a ſervice convenient to it, in order to the commending and maintenance of that its excellency: onely a created ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency was the object of this adoration. When Chriſtian ſubjects exhibite to the King acts of civil worſhip or adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as kneeling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they do this from a dutiful affection to God, and a like affection of love to their prince, which is Gods Vicegerent; yet they do not perform thoſe individual acts of adoration to God, in, by, or through him, that is, they do not perform them to God and the King, as two diſtinct ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of one and the ſame external, and of two diverſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adorations, but terminate them onely in the King. It is true, that the Fathers many times ſeemed to preſent the ſame individual acts both to God as ſymbols of their inward adoration of him, that is, of their affection of ſubmiſſion to the divine excellencies, and alſo to the croſs as ſymbols of their inward adoration of it, that is, of their affection of ſervice to its excellency, ſo uniting two inward coordinate adorations in one and the ſame external adoration: but whether ſo near a conjunction between the Divine and Eccleſiaſtical adoration, (if uſed indeed by them) proceeded from humane frailty, or may be defended by the Holy Scriptures, or be not diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to them, I refer to better conſideration.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid of the adoration of the croſs, may be eaſily applied to the like adoration of the relicks of Saints, of the Altar or Communion-Table by bowing,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 2 Cor. bom. 20. Et Baſil, Liturg.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the book of the Evangels by kiſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the like, which were uſed in the ſame time. It may be eaſily diſcerned that theſe adorations of the Croſs, Altars, Evangels, Relicks, and the like Eccleſiaſtical worſhipings were very lubrick,<note place="margin">Liturg. Chryſ.</note> ſo that it was a difficult matter to ſtand upright in them, and not to fall to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition or idolatry, as too many Churches did in after times.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 2 Cor. hom. 20.</note> The bowing to the Altar, which was done for the ſake of the Sacrament (which was much more to be partaker of the ſame adoration) when it became idolatrous, it eaſily advanced the Hereſy of Tranſubſtantiation. The degeneration likewiſe of the adoration of the Croſs and Relicks added to the former brought in, in ſubſequent times, the idolatrous adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of images.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93080:32"/>
            <p>And all theſe idolatrous adorations brought in the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous adoration of the name of Jeſus, either prolated or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; but not before about the year 1300.<note place="margin">Conc. Lugdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſ. an. 1374</note> Our Church ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted this laſt adoration of the name of Jeſus purged as much as might be from idolatry and ſuperſtition, reſtraining alſo the bowing to the naming of that comfortable name in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service. Yet it is a ſlippery Ceremony, and made the more ſlippery by the gloſs of ſome of our own Divines upon <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. Whence they would prove the bowing of our knee due to that bleſſed name Jeſus, affirming the Fathers ſo to expound that Text. To ſpeak in ſober ſadneſs and truth, there is not one Father that ſo expounds it, although you produce the Catalogue of the Fathers to ſweet and holy <hi>Bernard.</hi> There is not one Orthodox Author in all the length of that Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Fathers, who ſpeaks of any adoration given or to be given or exhibited to that moſt ſweet name Jeſus. The places produced by ſome late School-men out of the Fathers to make good their novel expoſition of that place in the Epiſtle of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> (which our men believed, and were thereby decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) have in them very ſmall appearance of proof, and nothing truth, as the inſpection of the places themſelves, (and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if compared with other plainer places of the ſame authors) will manifeſtly diſcover. All the latter School-men maintain that adoration of the good name Jeſus, whether ſpoken or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but all have not the braſen Foreheads to produce the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers as Patrons of it, or to expound the foreſaid text to prove it a duty. Let <hi>Vaſques</hi> a Learned Jeſuite be heard;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In p. 3. q. 25. diſp.</hi> 111. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> where it is ſaid (ſaith he) in the name of Jeſus let every knee be bowed, (ſo many Ancients read the text) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by name, not the word [Jeſus] but the thing it ſelf, that is, [Chriſt] is underſtood. And a little after he faith, out of this place it is not ſufficiently proved, that any honour (no not by accident) is to be exhibited to the word [Jeſus] writen or ſpoken, as to an image with its prototype. Therefore although there may be an innocency in thoſe adorations uſed in the right manner and ſenſe, yet it is hardly preſerved, (I had almoſt ſaid morally impoſſible) by the vulgar: it is ſo eaſie a lapſe from the uſe of one of them to fall to the uſe of the reſt, and then to the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93080:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>abuſe of every of them: For thoſe Eccleſiaſtical adorations of the altar, Evangels and the name Jeſus are uſed moſtly in the time of divine ſervice, when the like external acts of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration are exhibited to God, which near conjunction in time and place, between the one adoration and the other, and the beholding the ſame acts of worſhip to be done to God and a ſacred thing, doth puzzle the ignorant and unwary that either his zeal is as much to the creatures adoration, as to the Creators; or mingles in his mind both the adorations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the beſt is debaſed and corrupted.</p>
            <p>Some may ſay, may we not bow to God, and kneel to him at the altar, without danger? It is ſoon anſwered; That with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt we may, and muſt do ſo, and in ſo doing, our mind doth not intend the altar, as the object of our bowing: The danger is in bowing to the altar, for then we make it the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to which we bow.</p>
            <p>It may be demanded if the Magiſtrate make the naming of the name Jeſus, the name of the Saviour of the world, to be a ſign when, in the divine ſervice, we muſt bow to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Lord Jeſus, God and man, and not to the name Jeſus, may we not without danger ſo do? I anſwer, firſt, That it is our duty to bow our hearts, and alſo in convenient time and place, to bow our bodies to the man Jeſus Chriſt, in the unity of the divine perſon. And this is intended in <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. Secondly, to bow our bodies at the naming of the name of Jeſus is no duty that we are bound unto. It is indifferent then to bow or not to bow, as it is at the naming of the name of Chriſt. Thirdly, if the magiſtrate command us either at the naming of the name Jeſus, or at the naming of the name Chriſt in the divine ſervice, to worſhip Chriſt, God and man, by bowing unto him, and not intending the name [Jeſus] or [Chriſt] as an object of our bowing, it is our duty to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey our Superiours command. Fourthly, from the bowing [at] the name the vulgar eaſily fall to the bowing [to] the name.</p>
            <p>Theſe adorations of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> inward and outward may not be counted divine or properly and of their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, religious, becauſe no rule of true religion doth require
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93080:33"/>them, but they are properly Eccleſiaſtical, becauſe the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches did ſometime create them; and as things Eccleſiaſtical, and things any way made pertinent to religion, are counted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious things, ſo may theſe adorations be accidentally called religious. There is not that kind and degree of excellency in the Croſs, Communion-Table, or name Jeſus, or in any ſuch ſacred thing, which may in proper ſenſe merit and require that mental regard from us, which ſhould of right be teſtified by thoſe acts of worſhip. Neither do we find that the Churches acknowledged any obligation upon them, to make any Canon requiring thoſe adorations, but onely, as circumſtances then were, a congruity to command their uſe: under which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and judgement of the Church, individual perſons were to acknowledge thoſe ſacred things worthy thoſe honours. Wherefore if it pleaſe our Superiors to continue the uſe of theſe Ceremonies, which are ſo eaſily abuſed, it will be very neceſſary to ſtate and determine the right uſe of them, and to point at the dangers to be avoided, and to command that the cautions be at ſet times read in the Churches, that none may erre for want of knowledge, or by forgetfulneſs.</p>
            <p>The diſcreet followers of the holy ancient Fathers of the Church are worthy commendation, but their apes are ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. To ſow the foul raggs of ſome late ſlovenly School-men to the comely garment of our Church (as the miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the text in <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. have attempted) is an act diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful to the authors, derogating from the honour and dignity of our dear Mother and introductory of unwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adorations, being pretended to be commanded by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. For, if it be once obtained that the adoration uſed to the name Jeſus is of divine inſtitution, it will by the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of like reaſon follow, that the bowing to the croſs and the Communion-Table, and eſpecially, to the holy bread and wine, is a duty which of divine right doth belong unto them.</p>
            <p>But it is time to proceed to ſpeak of ſome other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Cuſtomes of the fourth Century,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17.</note> whereof one was derived from former times,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 2 Cor. hom. 2.</note> that in the Churches no Our Father was ſaid in the prayers, ſo long as the Catechumen and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93080:34"/>Penicents (for whom ſpecial prayers were made) were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſtay in the Church.<note place="margin">Concil. Leodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. can. <hi>19.</hi> Et Chryſoſt. in Eph. hom. <hi>3.</hi> Aug. de temp. ſer. <hi>38.</hi> Amalar. de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. miſſae c. <hi>19.</hi> Vide concil. Valentin. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> After their departure out of the Church began the <hi>ſecond divine Service</hi> and prayers proper to the faithful, among which was the Lords Prayer, moſt of the reſt were ſubſervient to the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper. When that Sacrament was to be adminiſtred (which was then uſually every Lords day) they offered bread and wine for the uſe of the Sacrament (inſtead of which we have offerings for the poor) and the Biſhop or Presbyter went from the Pulpit or place where he prayed for the penitents or his ſeat, to the Communion-Table; where it is to be noted, that he had not ſo long and difficult a journey to go, as in moſt parochial Churches the miniſter hath, to paſs from his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pew or Pulpit through a throng of people to the holy Table, and therefore there is good reaſon to ſpare him that labour in the days wherein is no Communion.</p>
            <p>Perſons excommunicated were nor received into Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of any Prayers in the Church,<note place="margin">Conc. Ancyram. can. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>25.</hi> Conc. Nicen. <hi>6.11.</hi>
               </note> no not with the Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, until they had humbled themſelves before the Biſhop, and earneſtly beſought that they might be made partakers of his councel, concerning what was needful to be done by them, to the perfecting of meet repentance in them, and whereby they might give ſufficient proof thereof, for the ſatisfaction of the Church offended by their tranſgreſſions, promiſing to follow his counſel, and to perform the enjoyned <hi>pennance.</hi> Upon this ſerious petition and promiſe the Biſhops and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters enjoyned ſuch works of unfained humiliation to be done by them, as they thought moſt agreeable for their caſe and condition, and praying for them admitted them to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and order of the Penitents. When theſe had fulfilled the enjoyned works of humiliation to be performed by them in that order, then they were admitted to the Communion of the prayers proper to the faithful, and after the works of repentance, which were commanded to be done by them in that rank, they were admitted to the Lords Supper, wherein was the perfection of Communion.<note place="margin">Conc. Nicen. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> If any Penitent in the courſe of humiliation was in an eminent and iminent danger of death, it was alway provided by the Fathers of the Church
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93080:34"/>that perfect Communion with the Church of God (without which Church is no ſalvation) ſhould be granted him in the participation of the body and blood of our bleſſed Saviour, except the governours of the Church had obſerved in him a very notorious defect in fulfilling his duty; of which yet if there was any the leaſt probable appearance of repentance, he was not denied the neceſſary <hi>viaticum</hi> (as the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> calls it.) The beſt men ready to depart to a better life deſired and took this caeleſtial meat for their comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment in their paſſage to God.</p>
            <p>Some miniſters are ſo ſtrict and parſimonious in giving the Holy Sacrament, that they deny the ſame unto a conſiderable part (yea often, to moſt part) of their pariſh, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had been admitted to it, without uſing the method pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by our Saviour in <hi>Matth.</hi> chap. 18. verſ. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>16, 17. Which text requires publick accuſation and proof in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the governours of the Church, and their publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation before the publick execution of ſo high a cenſure. They are alſo ſo hard hearted to dying men, earneſtly deſiring that ſoul-confirming &amp; moſt refreſhing <hi>viaticum,</hi> that although they cannot truely before God and men, (if put to it,) aſſure it, that they remain in a ſtate of ſin inconſiſtent with any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of ſaving grace, (as in caſe of denial, they ſhould be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good grounds aſſured) yet they can be ſo uncharitable and unmerciful, as to deny it unto them. Theſe extreams on the one hand, and on the other hand, partly the not forgotten great abuſe of the holy cenſures by Chancellors and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, partly the late ejecting of the ſet publick formes of prayers out of the Churches, and partly the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all the holy ordinances ſpread over the Kingdomes by the ſeveral Sects brought in and maintained by the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, to ſtrengthen and perpetuate themſelves, (if they could) in their moſt impious uſurpation and tyranny, theſe (I ſay) have made the Communion of Saints in the publick prayers, and the holy Sacraments, to be of very ſmall eſteem with moſt; inſomuch, that very many are brought to believe, they may go to heaven, notwithſtanding the neglect of them; for which moſt peſtilent diſeaſe, if ſeaſonable and convenient
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93080:35"/>medicine be not found out and wifely applied, the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be uncapable of receiving any benefit by the meer Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline; and the onely reſtraint under God againſt the growing ſad effects of irreligious profaneſs will lie in the ſole power of the Regal auctority.</p>
            <p>What geſture of body was uſed in thoſe ancient times in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the holy Communion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17.</note> whether ſtanding, or kneeling, or at ſome times the one, and at other times the other, is not very clearly and expreſſely ſet down by the writers of that age, that I can remember. This onely is certain, that they did not kneel in the receiving of it on the Lords days, becauſe it was againſt a Canon of the Church, to adore God by bowing of the knee on thoſe dayes: It is probable, that on other days (except in the <hi>Pentecoſt</hi>) they received kneeling,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Eſa. c. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> for St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſaith, that it was an Eccleſiaſtical Cuſtome to bow the knee to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Idem in Epiſt. ad Epheſ. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> which we may underſtand to be in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of that holy Sacrament, as well as in the publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; notwithſtanding that this holy Doctor ſaith in another place, that every one that is ſubject unto Chriſt, is ſaid to bend his knee unto him; and citing the words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> [at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhall be bowed] addeth, that the words do not pertain to the knees of the body, but to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the mind, and inclination of the ſoul, and obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſneſs of the heart to God: Which this moſt learned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would never have ſaid or written, if the Cuſtome of the Church had been in his time to kneel not onely unto Chriſt himſelf, but alſo to his name Jeſus, or if he had thought that this place of the Apoſtle did ſignifie it to be every mans duty to make the name Jeſus a co-object with Chriſt of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration by the bowing of the knee, as ſome of the latter Schoolmen have taught. In the time of St. <hi>Hierom</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the ſtanding in receiving the Euchariſt on the Lords day was accompanied with a low bowing of the body even nigh to a proſtration; for St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing upon the 98 <hi>Pſalm</hi> faith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſ. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> none eateth that fleſh, unleſs he firſt hath adored it. And in the words following he ſpeaketh of inclination and proſtration to that earth, that is, the fleſh of our Saviour (not conſidered as apart from, but as in, and with the moſt bleſſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93080:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Divine perſon.)<note place="margin">Cyrill. Hieroſol. Catech. Myſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſpeaking of the Holy Communion, ſaith, take the body of Chriſt ſaying <hi>Amen:</hi> and a little after, come (ſaith he) to the Cup of his blood, not extending thy hands, but incurving them (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and in manner of adoring and worſhiping, ſaying, <hi>Amen.</hi> But now, that the more urgent reaſons, which moved the Fathers of the Primitive Church not to uſe kneeling in adoring God on the Lords days, are ceaſed, it ſeems moſt convenient to kneel in taking the Holy Sacrament, upon what day ſoever we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; for the nearer Chriſt comes to us, and the more he doth deſcend and condeſcend in coming to us, yea, and into us, myſtically in thoſe external weak Elements, the more ſhould we deſcend, humble, and debaſe our ſelves by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bowing of our ſouls, and the external bending of our knees in the receiving of him, thereby teſtifying our own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs of that Grace, and commending the exceeding freeneſs of it. In the Kingdome of <hi>Preſter John</hi> they ſtand when they receive the holy Communion. In giving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the Biſhop or Presbyter ſaid,<note place="margin">Franciſc. Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus apud Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandri liturg. De Sacrament. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> the body of the Lord, and the receive ſaid, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> About the year 600, in the Sacramentary of <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, it is ſaid, while the prieſt giveth the Lords body, let him ſay, The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt preſerve thee to eternal life, <hi>Amen.</hi> And in giving the Cup let him ſay, The blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt preſerve thee to eternal life. In the maſs of ſome <hi>Armenians</hi> in <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> the prieſt communicating faith,<note place="margin">Apud Caſſand. liturg.</note> By faith I believe in the moſt holy Trinity the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt. By faith I eate thy quickning and ſaving body, O Lord Jeſus Chriſt; let it be unto me to the abſolution and remiſſion of my ſinnes. And in drinking the Cup, I drink by faith thy holy unmixed blood, blotting out ſins,<note place="margin">Apud Eundem.</note> O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for the remiſſion of my ſins, and of my Parents and of all the world. Every Communicant of the <hi>Armernians</hi> in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> goeth before the foot of the altar to receive. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in the Council of <hi>Laodic.</hi> before the year 400,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 19.</note> that only the miniſters might go in to the altar, and there take the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 17.</note> In the fourth Council of <hi>Tolet.</hi> it was appointed that the prieſts and deacons ſhould communicate before the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93080:36"/>altar, the ſubordinate Clergy in the Quire, the people without the Quire. This Council drave the people far off from the <hi>railes</hi> of the altar.</p>
            <p>Many more Rites and Ceremonies were uſed in the fourth Century, which do not pertain to our purpoſe, and very many more were afterward added; eſpecially in the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, we may perceive, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of our Divine Service book made choice of the beſt things out of the moſt ancient Liturgies of the Churches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18.</note> which flouriſhed long before the birth of Antichriſt, leaving many Ceremonies uſed in the primitive times, not very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to the preſent ſtate of our Churches, retaining other, that the garment of Chriſtian religion with us might not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vary from the ancient form ſo far as it could without prejudice to the body of religion be fitted to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that the ſolemnities and myſteries of Idols gained credit and reputation with men, by the ſumptuous rites and rich ornaments, whereby they were ſet forth and adorned. It is likely that the ancient Fathers, when miracles began to ceaſe, ſaw it expedient (for the removing of ſome of the obſtructions to Chriſtian faith) to add to the divine Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſome agreeable Rites, whereby the Chriſtian Doctrine might be commended to the rectitude of humane judgment, as not incredible or contemptible, and, it may be, thereby be commended as credible and worthy of good regard. The Schiſmaticks in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time,<note place="margin">Tertull. de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. baeret. c. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> (as he ſaith) named the decent Ceremonious Diſcipline of the Churches, a bawd, and counted the proſtration of that Diſcipline by themſelves to be Chriſtian ſimplicity: Whereas in very deed that proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of edifying order and Ceremonies, cauſed the confuſion of the holy ordinances among them, and ſluttiſhneſs in the celebrations of the divine inſtitutions; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> noted in thoſe Schiſmaticks, and we ſee now a days in ours. But on the other ſide we muſt remember, that we may erre (as in the defect, ſo) in the exceſs of Ceremonies, or in the choice, or in accounting and compelling others to own them for unchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable Apoſtolick inſtitutes, or by too rigid preſſing the uſe of every of them, eſpecially upon people of weak capacity,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:93080:36"/>humble, peaceable, and of a ſcrupulous conſcience.<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi> Placuit Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui S. nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud oneris im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam quae ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſario ſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re oportet. At quidam, haec nihil curantes, omnem quidem fornicationem pro nihilo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent: De Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus autem &amp; feriis &amp; inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis, perinde at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de anima ipſa, decertant, Dei mandata invertentes, &amp; ſibi ipſis leges ferentes, per Socrat. hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> Edit. Baſil. <hi>1570.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was grieved to ſee the tranſgreſſion of a Ceremony to be more ſeverely reprehended then the tranſgreſſion of Gods law: his judgment was, that the Ceremonies ſhould not be many, ſo as by them to preſs with ſervile burthens the Church of Chriſt, which God would preſerve free in the uſe onely of few Rites commended by manifeſt reaſons. Antiquity is venerable, yet it may not, ought not continue a Rite or Ceremony in any Church with whoſe edification and peace it is become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent. There be but few ordinances meerly Eccleſiaſtical, which have not in ſome Churches become noxious, or at leaſt uſeleſs. And there is a viciſſitude of profit or detriment growing from them many times in the ſame Churches, ariſing from notable changes in perſons and circumſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thought that thoſe obſervances which the whole Church kept, and no diverſity of manners had varied, were ordained by the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>110.</hi>
               </note> This his thought holds forth a probability and no demonſtration, for he himſelf in ſome place grants, that ſuch univerſal (and <hi>de facto</hi> unvaried) rites might have been made by a general Council, and we may add by cuſtome. Many Ceremonies were univerſal (as many then believed) and unvaried in <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s time, which were in following times, either altered, or altogether diſuſed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? ſurely becauſe they ceaſed to be uſeful, or became hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And therefore if St. <hi>Paul</hi> was the author of them, he gave them with conſent of the Churches to be uſed ſo long as they ſaw them to continue ſerviceable, or at leaſt not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Chriſtian religion. It was difficult in the ancient times to know which rites deſcended from the Apoſtles, and which not, or which were univerſal in ſuch an age by them that lived therein: They many times ſaid ſome Rites to be univerſal, which were ſo onely in the part of the Chriſtian world where they lived, as in the Eaſtern or Weſtern Churches.<note place="margin">Socrat. hiſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> Et Sozom. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>18, 19.</hi>
               </note> It was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewed, that many things were ſaid by the Fathers to be of divine or Apoſtolical inſtitution, which were not ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93080:37"/>if we ſpeak of divine or Apoſtolick inſtitutes in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſenſe: Sometime what was by one of the Fathers affirmed to be ſo, was by ſome other ancient writers referred to a more recent author,<note place="margin">De offic. Eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> as to one Pope or other. So ſome aſcribe the Roman Liturgy to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Iſidore,</hi> every part whereof is aſſigned to other authors by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, or <hi>Amalarius,</hi> or <hi>Alcuinus,</hi> or <hi>Strabus,</hi> or ſome other which have writen of the Roman Service. I find none to determine in particular what part of that Service was made by St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duran. ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale div. offic. pricip. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> but onely a few affirming that he compoſed three prayers of it. But if he had been the author of it as <hi>Iſidore</hi> relates, it is not to be doubted, but that the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches or moſt of them, had uſed onely that Liturgy. But the Church of <hi>Millaine</hi> had a proper Liturgy, the Churches of <hi>Spaine</hi> had another proper to them,<note place="margin">Concil. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levit. Can. <hi>12.</hi> Et Carth. <hi>3.</hi> Can. <hi>23.</hi> Cur cum una ſit fides, fint Eccleſiarum conſuetudines diverſae? &amp; altera conſuetudo miſſarum in Romana Eccleſia, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> altera in Gallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Eccleſiis teneatur? huic interrogationi Auguſtini Anglorum Epiſcopi ſic resp. Gregoriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Papa. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and the <hi>Africans</hi> had divers in divers Churches; ſome of which had unawares put into their Liturgy ſome prayers compoſed by Hereticks; which cauſed ſome <hi>African</hi> Councils to ordain, that no prayers ſhould be received into the Liturgy, but ſuch as were examined by Learned men or approved by a Council.<note place="margin">Novit fraternitas tua Romanae Eccleſiae conſuetudinem in qua ſe meminit eruditam; Sed mihi placet, ut ſive in Romana, ſive in Gallicana ſeu in qualibet Eccleſia aliquid inveniſti quod plus emnipotenti Deo poſſit placere, ſolicite eligas &amp; in Anglorum Eccleſia, quae adhuc ad fidem nova eſt, inſtitutione praecipua, quae de multis Eccleſiis colligere potuiſii, infundas. Non enim pro locis res ſed pro bonis rebus loca amanda ſunt. Ex quibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ergo Eccleſiis, quae pia, quae religioſa, quae recta ſunt, elige; &amp; haec quaſi in faſciculum collecta apud Anglorum mentes in conſuetudinem depone.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Every Church, at leaſt every Provincial Church, compoſed their prayers, or other parts of their divine Service, as ſeemed moſt conducible to their edification and after altered the ſame, or made a new form,<note place="margin">Vide Bern. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gienſ. de qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bud. rebus ad miſſam perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. c. <hi>2.</hi> Vide Sozom. hiſt. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> or received a form uſed in another Church, as they pleaſed: <hi>Spain</hi> or ſome part of it received the Roman Liturgy. And therefore if it ſhould ſeem good to the Church of <hi>England</hi> to mend their Liturgy, or compoſe a new one (if need be) more agreeable to the preſent time, they ſhould do therein no more then the moſt famous Churches have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93080:37"/>done before, and which can be no diſparaging of the wiſdome and piety of the Compoſers of it, which intended onely to make it as fit as could be for the ſtate of the Church in their time (which I believe they performed very exactly) and not to frame and impoſe an unchangeable form which could never prove incongruous to any poſſible variety in the ſtate of the Church; for this is not in the power of any perſons or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Howſoever Ceremonies and a form of Liturgy, are no more neceſſary for Epiſcopal, then a Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may equally erre in defect or exceſs, or quality of the rites and divine Service.</p>
            <p>Now although both the forms of government and all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical rites be in their nature changeable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 19.</note> becauſe of their dependance upon variable circumſtances, yet ſome have been leſs ſubject to change or abrogation then other, either becauſe they be of ſmal efficacy to hurt or profit, or becauſe the hurt done by them is hardly diſcerned, or becauſe the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which are apt to make them noxious, ſeldome happen, or becauſe they are believed to have the Apoſtles for their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors or approvers.</p>
            <p>Of all other, Epiſcopacy ſeems leaſt ſubject to abrogation. Firſt, becauſe the Churches in all parts of the world, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways firmly perſwaded, that the inſtitution of Epiſcopacy, had the Apoſtles hand and ſeal joyned with the mother Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for the confirmation of it. Secondly, becauſe many believed that the Apoſtles never permitted the Colledge of Presbyters to ordain Presbyters in the time that they ruled in the Churches, this they received by tradition, to which they eaſily gave their aſſent, becauſe they found not in the Acts of the Apoſtles, or the Apoſtolical Epiſtles, that ſole Presbyters ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any (except perhaps by an immediate command of the Holy Ghoſt, which is extraordinary) but with a Preſident ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Apoſtle or an Evangeliſt, or a Vicegerent of an Apoſtle, as <hi>Timothy, Titus, &amp;c.</hi> whence they thought it might be very probably collected, that the Apoſtles would have given a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality of the exerciſe of the power of ordination unto one Presbytet onely in every Church, ſo as without him the whole Colledge could not ordain, and would have left the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93080:38"/>to be exerciſed in common, equally by all, if the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had not ſo groſly abuſed their ruling power, whereby it was ſeen that the Colledge had need of a Preſident both in the Government, and the Ordination, which was accordingly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by the decree of the Church, approved by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. St. <hi>Hierome</hi> himſelf hath ſome paſſages, which ſeem to favour this opinion,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i paſſim om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus (Preſh.) eſſes conceſſum (ordinare,) tot admitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur ad or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, quod non ſervaretur ordo; immo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius generare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur confuſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: &amp; ideo diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt Dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie, quod ſolis Epiſcopis ordinum diſpenſatio &amp; aliorum officiorum, ut conſecratio abbatum, monialium &amp; eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; conſimilium concedatur. Bonevent. in <hi>4. d. 25.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and therefore the Churches never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a Presbyter, or Chor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſcope, to ordaine, except he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the place of a Biſhop, when he could not be preſent, and the Ordination could not be delayed; Thirdly, The Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Government was in uſe in the pureſt purity of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, beginning to ſpread abroad over the world by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles, and yet in leſs then twenty years ſpace Schiſmes grew out of it, which cauſed the Churches to out it, and to eſtabliſh Epiſcopacy as the beſt antidote againſt Schiſme, and for the reſtauration and maintenance of the Churches peace.</p>
            <p>Now if the Presbyterian Government was uneffectuall for the preſerving of peace among the moſt godly, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the moſt addicted to peace, who can expect it ſhould be effectuall to reſtore union and peace, and to preſerve it in Churches too full of pollutions and ſtaines, very much dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the holineſs of the Apoſtolicall times? It ſeems a deſperate and prepoſterous courſe, to uſe that as a ſoveraigne Antidote in our time, which had the effect of a Poyſon upon the Churches in the Apoſties time. A hurnt Child dreads the fire; and ſhould not the weaker members of the body dread the fire, that burnt the ſtrongeſt and beſt able to reſiſt its force? Seeing the remainder of naturall corruption in the moſt holy Churches drew the Poyſon of Sciſme from the Presbyterian forme of government, we cannot, without high preſumption, think that the far higher degrees of ſin remaining in us, will be idle, &amp; ſuffer grace to make of it an Antidote againſt Schiſme. Mountebanks are ſeen ſometime to heal by improper Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, where the ſtrength of nature, and the concurrence of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93080:38"/>ſome other ſecret cauſes do performe the cure, and not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Phyſick. So may the Presbyterian government have in ſome place the credit of healing Schiſmes &amp; maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace, when in very truth thoſe good effects proceed from the confluence of other cauſes, and not from the aptneſs of that government to effect them: For it ſeems incredible that it ſhould have in it an aptneſs to keep us in peace, that had in it an ineptitude to keep the moſt peaceably diſpoſed Apoſtolick Chriſtians in unity and peace. Whence we may conclude, that although the ancient Epiſcopacy be in its nature changeable, as being of the Churches, and by conſequence of humane conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, yet morally and practically it may not be abrogated without dammage to the Church; which will aſſuredly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, if ſome accidentall benigne influences of ſome other cauſes do not for ſome time hinder its birth.</p>
            <p>I am very apt to believe, that the Churches, which ſeem to uſe the Presbyterian government, never intended by any Law, deſerving the proper name of a Law, to ſettle the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Presbytery in their Churches, whence the ſad Schiſmes aroſe in the primitive times; much leſs to abrogate the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Epiſcopacy, which in the judgment of the beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and of the Apoſtles, is the healer of Schiſmes, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of peace: But that they intended (as they had good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) to abrogate the corrupted Hierarchy, with the multitude of its oppreſſing attendants, and (as neceſſity compelled them) ſeemingly to ſuſpend their reception of the ancient Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but in very deed receiving in ſome hidden ſort the ſubſtance of it, ſecretly giving that Authority to the moderator of the Colledge of Presbyters, which tantamounts the Authority of the ancient Biſhops. This was done by them in their Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, out of the Gulfe of the Babyloniſh Idolatry and Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, when the ſtate of perſons and Circumſtances would not permit them directly and manifeſtly to ſet up the ancient Epiſcopacy, but covertly and cloathed with the apparel of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery; Becauſe the appearing of it in its native cloathing ſeemed to threaten an extreme danger of returning again to Idolatrous <hi>Babylon.</hi> Thus when two duties became inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, the keeping out of Idolatry, and the open and manifeſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93080:39"/>uſe of an Ordinance inferior to the maintenance of the purity of Gods worſhip; they did, as it was their duty, ſo far forbear the open uſe of Epiſcopacy as ſeemed needfull, that they might preſerve the truth and ſincerity of the worſhip of God. I know many writers are of another mind, but the intentions of Churches are better ſeen in the cauſes of their actions, and the managing of them, then in the letter of a Law, or in the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative opinions of private perſons.</p>
            <p>Some think the preſent condition of our Church, to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the ſame with the ſtate of thoſe Churches, when they firſt began their Reformation, and therefore that we ſtand in need of the ſame cure under the habit of the Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Surely theſe are much deceived; firſt, in their opinion of our preſent ſtate; ſecondly, in the ſequele, if our caſe were like theirs: for, when we were like them in departing from <hi>Babylon,</hi> we were unlike them in many other reſpects, and needed not the habit of Presbyters, but fall to purge the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Epiſcopacy from as many of the foul excreſcencies which the ſins of men made to grow to it, as the condition of that time would permit, whereby our Church kept more uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the primitive Churches, and by the bleſſing of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our endevour, obtained more meaſure of the Heavenly light, and of the power of Godlineſs in peace, and that for a longer time, then any part of thoſe Churches attained unto, which were neceſsitated to ſhrowd themſelves under another habit of Government. This I ſay not any way to diſparage any other Church of Chriſt, (whom I honour and pray for from my heart) or to aſcribe any thing to our own wiſdome and providence, but to honour and glorifie the grace of God for his great mercies to our Church, and to defend her honour againſt the miſtakes of ſome.</p>
            <p>But now our condition is changed our ſins have brought us to miſery, the light and glory of our Church is turned to dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, confuſion, and contempt; from which (notwithſtanding our unworthineſs) Gods infinite mercy (which hath moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly reſtored our Soveraign Lord the King unto his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Subjects) will be pleaſed, I truſt, to deliver us, and to beautifie our Church with the primitive Apoſtolicall Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93080:39"/>attended by his aſſeſſors and Senate, the reverend, grave, wiſe, learned and pious Colledg of Presbyters, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the houſe of God, after the beſt pattern of the primitive holy orders and diſcipline, for the obtaining whereof, God would have us aſſiſted by His grace to contribute our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, improved to the uttermoſt of Chriſtian Wiſdom and moderation, to be crowned with his rich bleſſing. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this buſineſs is about things for the moſt part ſpirituall, tending to the edification of Gods houſe, it will, no doubt, pleaſe our gracious King and his great Councell not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this work without the adviſe and counſell of them, whom Chriſt hath ordained under Himſelf Miniſter all buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of His Houſe; leaſt the neglect of His Ordinance and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters cauſe the Lord to blaſt all other Counſells and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, how probable ſoever they may ſeem to be in the eye of the world. Give unto <hi>Caſar</hi> the things which are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and let the Vicegerents of Chriſt enjoy the things belonging to them, let all intereſts have their due part in this weighty work; and then whatſoever Government be ſettled, what form ſoever of Divine ſervice, what Rites ſoever and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſhall be eſtabliſhed, they will with all readineſs and due ſubmiſſion be received and embraced by all the people, and all the obedient Sons and Daughters of our deareſt Mother the Church of <hi>England:</hi> among whom if there ſhall be ſome whoſe judgments cannot acquieſce in ſome determinations of the higher powers, they will wiſely conſider; firſt, that in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote concluſions of Divine maximes, all good men in this our infirmity will never agree, and that nature teacheth us that in controverſies the reſolution of the major part muſt be obeyed, without which debates would never be ended, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, let the ſpirits of the Prophets be ſubject to the Prophets. Secondly, That God hath appointed the powers civil and Eccleſiaſticall in his ſtead to determine Eccleſiaſticall contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and to make Eccleſiaſticall Ordinances, from whoſe judgment there is no appeal but only to God by prayer. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That to preſerve the peace of the Church and Charity the bond of perfectneſs, is a duty to be preferred before the duty of publick teaching, divulging, or preaching many of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93080:40"/>Truths, whoſe ignorance (if not voluntary) doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from Heaven, when that teaching or publiſhing doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the publick peace, and conſequently the keeping of the peace requireth abſtinence in that caſe from ſuch divulging or preaching.</p>
            <p>And from theſe conſiderations good men will infer that it is good for them, and that it is their duty both for the ſake of Gods Authority, for good order ſake, and for Charity and peace ſake, &amp; out of a Conſcientious regard to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to acquieſce in their determinations, and to deſiſt from oppoſing their private opinion to the publick judgment, and purſuing their private intereſt to the prejudice of publick peace and Charity. For which Wiſedome and moderation, that they may be in all, let all good men pray to the onely wiſe and moſt mercifull God, the Author of Truth and peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An APENDIX.</head>
            <p>THe manner of the Ordination of Biſhops (forgotten to be ſhewed by me in due place) is declared by the fourth Councill of <hi>Carthage</hi> in theſe words;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 2.</note> When a Biſhop is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, lay and hold the book of the Evangeliſts upon his head and neck, and one Biſhop pronouncing the Benediction over him, let the reſt of the Biſhops preſent touch his head with their hands. The Church never accounted any to be capable of this Epiſcopall Ordination that was not firſt ordained a Presbyter, the manner of whoſe Ordination, was that the Biſhop bleſſing him (ſaying, <hi>receive the Holy Ghoſt, whoſoever ſins you ſhall remitt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil earth. Can <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c.) and laying his hand upon his head, the Presbyters preſent lay their hands upon his head by the hand of the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>There was a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Tert. de praeſcript. c. <hi>41.</hi> Cyprian. Epiſt. ad Antonianum Hier. ad Heliodorum Conc. Sardicenſ. c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Canon in uſe in the ſecond Century (when
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93080:40"/>it was made it is not known) which required that every one that would be an Eccleſiaſticall Officer ſhould begin with; and for ſome ſet time officiate in the loweſt Office, and ſo by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees aſcend to the Epiſcopacy, if the Church did deſire his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement. Yet we find that ſome laicks, yea ſome unbaptiſed perſons have been by the Clergy and people choſen Biſhops, as <hi>Ambroſe, Nectarius,</hi> and other,<note place="margin">Paulinus in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Ambroſij. Niceph. Calliſt. Eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> who leaping over the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour offices, and the time wherein they ſhould have given proofe of their faithfulneſs and induſtry in the order of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, have been Baptiſed, made Presbyters, and then Biſhops within few dayes, and ſome (it may be) took theſe two laſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the ſame houre. But this was very rare, and by diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or was liable to an Eccleſiaſticall cenſure.</p>
            <p>When any under the degree of a Presbyter, was by the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or perverſneſs of ſome Biſhops, ordained a Biſhop, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing done by him was eſteemed valid, but what his former degree did warrant, or a Laick might in neceſſity do, untill he was made a Presbyter. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith truly, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that one ſhould be ordained a Biſhop <hi>(fit to officiate)</hi> which was not before a Presbyter, or did not take both orders together. For (ſaith he) Epiſcopacy includes Presbytery in its eſſence, and a Biſhop, no Presbyter, is a figment,<note place="margin">De Sacramento Ordinis. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> a Biſhop being nothing elſe but the firſt or chief Presbyter. Whence he doth rightly infer that the Ordination of a Biſhop, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Ordination of a Presbyter, is (being in it ſelf preciſely conſidered) inferior to it, as being of no efficacy as to acts meerly Eccleſiaſticall, and which the civil Magiſtrate cannot execute.</p>
            <p>Here ſome doubts are raiſed which by divers are diverſely reſolved. As whether Chriſt did ordaine the Apoſtles in the firſt place Presbyters, and after that Biſhops? and if ſo, when was this done? or if it be ſaid that Chriſt made them Apoſtles, Presbyters and Biſhops, in one and the ſame Ordination, how can it be proved that Chriſt gave the Apoſtles the powers now proper to Biſhops, not only as they were extraordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but alſo as they were to have ſucceſſors; and not rather that Chriſt reſerved thoſe powers as they were to be conveyed by ſucceſſion to be given in a more convenient time? it is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93080:41"/>generally acknowledged that Presbyters were vertually or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained when the Apoſtles were ordained. If Chriſt made the Apoſtles both Presbyters and Biſhops in one Ordination, how durſt the Church alter our Saviours Ordinance, as to ordain them by two actuall Ordinations whom He Himſelf had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in one virtuall Ordination? to ſay that our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ordained the Apoſtles firſt Presbyters, and afterwards Biſhops, is to affirm that which the Evangeliſts do not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To Preach, Baptiſe, adminiſter the Lords Supper, to feed the Sheep, to bind and looſe, all theſe offices appear by clear Teſtimonies of the holy Scriptures, and the conſent of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church to belong to Presbyters; and therefore it may not be reaſonably thought that any of thoſe places of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts which promiſe thoſe powers, or intimate them to be given, or require the execution of them, conveigh an Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Apoſtles ſuppoſed before ordained Presbyters. Some ſay, that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and ſome other of the Fathers affirm Chriſt in ordaining the Apoſtles to have ordained Biſhops, and that Biſhops are the Apoſtles ſucceſſors, and Presbyters the ſucceſſors of the 70 Diſciples. To theſe Objections the anſwers are ready and eaſie.<note place="margin">Ad Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in Pſ. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt by his Apoſtles conſtituted and ordained Biſhops, and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, that the Church conceived Biſhops, neither of them writeth that Biſhops were vertually ordained in the Apoſtles Ordination, neither is this expreſly ſaid in any anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Author.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> ad Timoth, <hi>c. 3.</hi>
               </note> Secondly, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> the contemporary or elder then the true <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, that the Ordination of a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Biſhop is one and the ſame, this may ſeem ſtrange, for in his and the preceding times, they were diſtinct, but his following words declare his meaning when he gives this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, namely,<note place="margin">Cyprian ad florentium, &amp;c. Epiſt.</note> becauſe both Presbyter and Biſhop are <hi>Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> Prieſts, which ſhews that in ſaying, that the Ordination of a Presbyter and Biſhop is the ſame, he meant <hi>quatenus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes,</hi> as they were Prieſts or Presbyters, their ordination was the ſame.</p>
            <p>So the other auncient Doctors which ſay that Chriſt in ſpeaking ſome things to the Apoſtles, as, <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil. conſtit. monaſt. <hi>c. 22.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpake in and by them to Biſhops, or that in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93080:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>them Chriſt ordained Biſhops, did mean, That our Saviour ſpake in and by the Apoſtles to Biſhops, (not as Biſhops) but as they were <hi>Sacerdotes,</hi> Prieſts, and Presbyters, and only conſequently and remotely, by the means of a ſubſequent Ordinance, as they were Biſhops, that is, Presbyters, having a preſidency over their Brethren, when the Paſtors of that primitive Church ſay, that Biſhops are Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, and Presbyters ſucceſſors of the 70 Diſciples, their meaning was, That having reſpect to the Diſtinction which the Apoſtles made, between one Presbyter and the reſt, by exalting one in every Church to a preſidency over the reſt: The Preſident Presbyter, which is the Biſhop, ſucceeds the Apoſtles, whoſe Succeſſors, and the ſubject Presbyters ſucceeded the 70 Diſciples, in ſome likeneſs of ſuperiority and inferiority.</p>
            <p>The Fathers could not mean, That the Presbyters were ordained in the Ordination of the 70. For</p>
            <p>Firſt, None of them had any good ground to affirm, That the 70 either had ſo ample an ordinary power (if they had any ordinary power) as the Presbytery have; or that the power they received was rather the power of an Office to continue in them,<note place="margin">Ad Rodolphum Archiepiſcopum Senonenſ. in apparandarum rerum addend. poſt <hi>tom. 7. Concil.</hi>
               </note> then a power only to do ſome acts for a certain time after, which the power was to leave them, although Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the firſt affirms, That the 70 Diſciples had the Offices of Biſhops, and could ordain Presbyters.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Form of Ordination, both in our Church, and in the Roman pontificial, doth manifeſtly ſhew, That Presbyters were virtually ordained in the Ordination of the Apoſtles, after our Saviours Reſurrection, when he ſaid, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt, Whoſeſoever ſins ye remit,</hi> &amp;c. the which entire words are uſed in Presbyters Ordination, and only one member of the words are uſed in the ordination of biſhops, that is, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which words do not ſerve to conveigh unto them all power to remit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they had received in their Ordination, to Presbytery, but they ſerve to give them the power of Preſidency, whereby the Biſhop is conſtituted: and therefore Presbyters and Biſhops, as they be Presbyters, are the primary Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, and Biſhops, as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93080:42"/>Biſhops, that is, as to their preſidency are onely ſecondary Succeſſors of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>There is no great cauſe of doubt whether thoſe words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid, uſed at this time in the ordination of Biſhops or Presbyters,<note place="margin">Cum Eccleſia in ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſacerdotum Chriſtum imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata ritu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuo eiſd. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; forma il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, Accipite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum Sanctum quorum remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeritis peccata, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Semper u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa fuerit, quis ambigat idem omnino quod Chriſtum face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <hi>&amp;c. Vaſq.</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> p. diſp. <hi>239.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> were together with impoſition of hands therein uſed in and from the Primitive times, becauſe they are not expreſſely mentioned in any ancient Author, for a thouſand years and above (for any thing I could learn) for firſt the Fathers do often ſay, that impoſition of hands was uſed in thoſe ordinations (and ought to be uſed) as alſo a benediction and prayers: which prayers (no queſtion) were accommodated in each ordination to the diſtinction made by the Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Presbyters and Biſhops, and therefore the words [<hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt, whoſoevers ſins ye remit,</hi> &amp;c.] might be uſed in the prayers of the Biſhops ordination, for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the grace and power received by them in their Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial ordination, and omitted in the prayers of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ordination (wherein they conſtitute the benediction,) becauſe the fulneſs of the exerciſe of the power given by the miniſtery of thoſe words, and other parts of their ordination is ſomething reſtrained by the conſtitution of Epiſcopacy.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why thoſe holy men did not ſet down in their writings the very words of benediction ſpoken at the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 2 Cor. <hi>hom.</hi> 6.</note> and the particular forms of prayers then uſed is declared by <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nota, patres &amp; concilia non conſueviſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicare totum ritum Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum (non enim ſcribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant libros ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuales) ſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum attigiſſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam partem eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentialem ex qua caetera omnia intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerentur. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm.</hi> de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. Ord. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> who, ſpeaking of Biſhops begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Act of ordination, ſaith, That ſuch and ſuch words were ſpoken which the initiated knew, for it is not lawful (ſaith he) to detect all before the profane.</p>
            <p>As for the forms of Ordination which were written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the years 700 and 1000 and the forms in <hi>Clements</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, beſides that they are of ſmall credit, they are imperfect and diſagree among themſelves. In one form of Biſhops conſecration the book is not remembred to be held over the head of the perſon to be ordained; in another form there is no mention of the impoſition of hands. In a form of the ordination of a Presbyter, the Biſhop and Presbyters holding their hands on the head of the ordained, it is ſaid, <hi>&amp; det orationem ſuper eum,</hi> and let the Biſhop pray above him,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93080:42"/>then many ſorts of prayers follow. Whence we may gather, that the prayer to be made over him differs from the other prayers, and that under the word [Prayer] the words of benediction, which are, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt, Whoſoever ſins ye remit,</hi> &amp;c. are comprehended. For thoſe words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the Biſhop as the mouth of the Church are a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual prayer; the heavenly gift ſignified by them,<note place="margin">Manus impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones verba ſunt myſtica quibus confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur ad opus electus accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens auctorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem teſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia ſua, ut audeat vice Domini ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium Deo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> in Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> ad <hi>Timoth.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> Homo imponit. manus, Deus largitur gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, homo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem dexteram, &amp; Deus bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicit potenti dextera. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ.</hi> de digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſacerd. <hi>a Greg.</hi> Epiſt. l. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> and to be given in the uſe of them, being begged of God in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, and alſo in the ſubſequent prayers. And as they are pronounced by the Biſhop ſupplying the place and inſtead of Chriſt, they are Chriſts benediction, and a ſignification of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative will in giving the Holy Ghoſt unto ſome (that's Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in their ordination) to authoriſe them to do the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal acts of binding and looſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to accompany thoſe acts duely exerciſed in the union and communion of the true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church; and unto others (that is, Biſhops, in their ordination) to authorize and enable them for the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, univerſal, and preſidential uſe and adminiſtration of the power of binding and looſing before received in their Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial ordination, and for the ſole exerciſe of the power of ordination, and to accompany their ſervice duely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the union and communion of the true Church of Chriſt. So the words of the inſtitution of the Lords Supper are in themſelves no prayers, but conſidered as a part of the prayer preceding them (called by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, the Canon, which is not reputed to be ended before thoſe words be prolated) they are a virtual prayer being preſented unto God in the ſupplication of the Church for the obtaining of an heavenly effect in the imitation of the act of Chriſt like unto that effect which was granted at the act of prolation of them by Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Major</hi> &amp; <hi>Angel.</hi> affirm, that they ſaw ſome Pontificals which were both without the words [<hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.] and alſo without impoſition of hands. Therefore thoſe omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are no ſufficient arguments to prove that the foreſaid words of benediction were not uſed in the Primitive times. We may further prove them to be then in uſe by this, that of all the integral parts of Presbyters ordination, we find
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93080:43"/>nothing proper to the Biſhop,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſil. <hi>ad</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philock. <hi>Can.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> but onely thoſe words of benediction; for the Presbyters impoſe their hands as well as the Biſhops, the Presbyters and people faſt and pray with the Biſhop, there's nothing left but the prolation of the words of benediction, in the name and place of Chriſt. This is confirmed by the ſtory of the purblind Biſhop, who having laid his hand to ordain a Presbyter, and the Presbyters their hands, uſed the eyes and mouth of a Presbyter to read and pronounce the benediction.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cone.</hi> Hiſpal. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> Its not ſaid that the Presbyter read the prayers (although its moſt likely he read them) but the benediction. And why? ſurely becauſe the prayers were the common prayers of the whole Church, and the benediction onely proper to the Biſhop, and therefore that ordination was rejected as unlawful and invalid, a Presbyter and not a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop having prolated the benediction: and the Biſhops com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was of no value, becauſe prohibited by the Canons in force at that time. Above 300 years before this Biſhop, in the time of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> all the Presbyters (and <hi>Iſchyras</hi> among them) which were ordained by <hi>Colythus</hi> a pretended Biſhop, were refuſed to be received by the Church in that degree,<note place="margin">Athanaſ. <hi>in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</hi> 2.</note> becauſe <hi>Colythus</hi> was proved to be onely a Presbyter, whoſe ordination, in the judgment of the Church, the conſtitution of the Apoſtles had made invalid.<note place="margin">Serm. de extel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. ſacrorum Ord.</note> 
               <hi>Ivo Carnotenſis</hi> ſpeaking of the ordination of Presbyters, and having ſaid, that the Biſhop and Presbyters had laid their hands, he adds, and they invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Holy Ghoſt upon them which are ordained; where he leaves nothing proper for the Biſhop but the words of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction prolated by him, and onely by him as in the place of Chriſt. The Biſhop invocated in the name of the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and bleſſed in the name and place of our Saviour. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writing to a Biſhop whom he had ordained,<note place="margin">Epiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> ad Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum Comenſem.</note> ſaith, the ordination which thou haſt received by the impoſition of my hands, and benediction in the name of the Lord Jeſus is not reprehended.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>in</hi> Eſa. <hi>c.</hi> 58.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith that ordination is not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled onely by imprecation of the voyce, but alſo by impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hand. Now becauſe the benediction was and ought to be ſaid, while the Biſhop and Presbyters (in the ordination of theſe) impoſe and hold their hands on the head of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93080:43"/>perſon to be ordained (the formal prayer going before the impoſition and following after it,) and becauſe it is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal part of the ordination, to which the impoſition of hand is ſubſervient, as it is a vertual prayer, St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De baptiſ. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Donatiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> what is impoſition of hand, but a prayer over a man? And as it is ſpoken by the Biſhop in Chriſts ſtead, delivering the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical power in Chriſts name, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>Timoth.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> that the impoſition of hands are myſtical words whereby the elect <hi>(to the office of the ſacred miniſtery)</hi> receiving authority is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed for his work, that he may be bold to offer Sacrifice to God in Chriſts ſteed. Whereby we ſee that impoſition of hand, and the benediction, are diſtinct parts of ordination, yet ſo conjunct, and the benediction ſo excelling the impoſition of hand, that the whole is reckoned nothing elſe but a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or prayer.</p>
            <p>I confeſs that I did ſometime begin to ſuſpect, that when the Roman Court had determined ordination to be a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment properly ſo called, as baptiſm, and inſtituted by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, they put in thoſe words in the ſolemnity of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the better confirmation and propagation of their new opinion; but conſidering the reaſons aforeſaid, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that the bleſſed Reformers of our Church have retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame words, and nothing doubting but that in ſo doing they did not favour the popiſh opinion, but were perſwaded they did therein follow their pattern, which was the uſage of the Primitive Church, I rejected that conceit and ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>The firſt Author that I can remember to have read, more expreſſely intimating the ſaid words of benediction to be uſed in the ordination of Presbyters, is our Country-man <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hale,</hi> in theſe words;<note place="margin">Summ. part. <hi>4.</hi> q. <hi>21.</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> the Keyes (ſaith he) are given with the ſacerdotal order, when it is ſaid, <hi>whoſe fins you remit,</hi> &amp;c. and when a Biſhop is conſecrated, another Key is not conferred upon him, but the uſe of that firſt Key is extended. Thus far he, who flouriſhed about the year 1240.</p>
            <p>In the words [<hi>Whoſe ſins ye remit,</hi> &amp;c.] remiſſion muſt not be taken preciſely for the taking away the guilt of ſin, or the reconciling of paenitents upon their private or publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for ſins committed after baptiſm, but alſo for the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93080:44"/>taking away the power and raign of ſin, which is done by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed grace, which having removed the ſpiritual darkneſs and death, illuminates the ſoul, and makes it alive to God. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of the Presbyterial function, tends to this laſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as well as to the former, although one paſtoral office may be more eſpecially directed to the former, and another in a more ſpecial manner to the latter effect.</p>
            <p>The Fathers do often apply thoſe words in St. <hi>John</hi> now frequently remembred, and the like in <hi>Matth.</hi> ch. 16. and chap. 18. to the act of reconciling Paenitents to God and the Church, and much oftner then they do to any other kind of the miniſterial looſing or remiſſion, and they had good reaſons moving them ſo to do. For, firſt, Haereticks began in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Century to deny that Chriſt left any miniſterial power in his Church for the remiſſion of any great ſin committed after baptiſm; and this Hereſie was revived by <hi>Novatian</hi> and <hi>Novatus</hi> in the third Century, and quickned by the Donatiſts in the fourth Century. Againſt which, the Orthodox Paſtors of the Church uſed thoſe places of Scripture, to prove that the power of reconciling ſuch Penitents was given to the Church of Chriſt. Secondly, the zeal of the people in the Primitive Times, and the encouragements of the Miniſters, and after, the Canons of the Church inclined the people to make confeſſion of their ſecret enormities to the Church or Paſtors (not becauſe neceſſary to ſalvation, but becauſe it was found very profitable as the times and perſons were then qualified,) and publick offendors were brought to publick repentance, and (this being duely performed) were publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reconciled to God and his Church. Theſe things being ſo frequent and ſolemn, yet very irkſome and grievous to fleſh and blood, it was very neceſſary for the Fathers of the Church to put the people dayly in mind of the benefit of thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and penitence, and the neceſſity of both as to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous offences in order to a publick reconciliation, which they could not otherwiſe do better then by making uſe of thoſe places of Scripture for the Demonſtration and proof of the peoples Duty, and the certainty and comfort of their reconciliation.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:93080:44"/>
            <p>None of thoſe holy Paſtors denyed the miniſterial power of remiſſion or looſſing to be exerciſed in the other miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial offices, inſtituted as the means which God would bleſs (if not abuſed) for the begetting and increaſing of ſaving grace. Yea ſome of them have expreſſely taught, that the preaching of the word, baptiſm, and conſequently the Lords Supper are Keyes which open Heaven to ſome, and ſhut Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt others, and are the inſtruments of Gods power to looſe ſome from the bonds of the guilt and power of ſin, and to bind thoſe that refuſe to be looſed by them. For, doth not the Lords Supper bind the unworthy receivers, who eat and drink their own damnation! and doth it not ſet at liberty and open Heaven to them, who in eating and drinking ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of Chriſt eat and drink their own ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? but lets hear what holy <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, the Apoſtles do looſe men (ſaith he) by the words of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Eſa. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> the teſtimony of the Scriptures and exhortation of vertues.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dib. q. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> And again in another place, the Apoſtles (ſaith he) in the firſt day of Chriſts reſurrection received the grace of the Holy Ghoſt, whereby they might remit ſins and baptiſe and make ſons of God, and give the ſpirit of adoption to believers, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf ſaying, <hi>Whoſoevers ſins ye remit, they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi> Thus far <hi>Hierome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The powers promiſed unto St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> ch. 16. and the powers given unto the Apoſtles, when our Saviour breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them and ſaid, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c. and the powers mentioned in the 18 chap. of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> ſuppoſed before given, or to be in a ſpecial manner given in time to come, are one and the ſame powers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> de ſacerdotio. l. <hi>3. Ambroſ.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aenit. c. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>6. Hier.</hi> ad <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liod.</hi> de vita ſolit. <hi>Athanaſ.</hi> ſerm. in illud [p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti in pagum, &amp;c.] <hi>Cypr.</hi> de ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Praelat.</note> and ſo taken to be by the Doctors of the Primitive Church, which they do unanimouſly acknowledge to be given unto the Apoſtles both in right and poſſeſſion (as to the eſſential parts of the powers) before Chriſts death: although there is ſome ſeeming variety among them concerning the punct of time before his death, wherein Chriſt gave them declaratively unto them, and the immediate ſubject to whom they were given.</p>
            <p>Conſidering their ſayings concerning this matter, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them together, and ſo expounding them that they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:93080:45"/>may agree with the Scriptures and among themſelves, theſe following aſſertions may be gathered from them. Firſt, They do not deny the ſaid powers to have been given (as to their eſſentials) unto the Apoſtles when he called them to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, and gave them the name of Apoſtles; For they could not think, that Chriſt gave them the name of the office, without the office it ſelf: And it appears that the Apoſtles preached and baptiſed before the promiſe of them was made unto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> They received with the name of Apoſtles the powers to miniſter all the doctrine and means of ſalvation which Chriſt intended in due time to deliver unto them.<note place="margin">Act. 1.24, 25. Act. 26.16.</note> And therefore when the Sacrament of the Euchariſt was inſtituted, they needed not a new ordination, but onely a ſignification of Chriſts pleaſure, that they ſhould uſe the power before given them in the adminiſtration of this ordinance, which is but an extention of the power to a new object. Secondly, they agree,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in <hi>Joh.</hi> hom. <hi>85. Cyprian.</hi> de ſimplicit. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latoruus. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, &amp; civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei c. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; quaeſt. ex vet. &amp; Novi Teſtam. c. <hi>93.</hi>
               </note> that all the Apoſtles received thoſe powers when our Saviour breathed upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that this was a ſolemn or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of them, giving them more grace to accompany their miniſtery then they had in their firſt call and leſs ſolemn or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, or in the ſubſequent manifeſtation thereof before his death. This is the more proper ordination of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the new teſtament, the full original and ſeminal tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the miniſterial powers, whereby all future ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the like kind are ſanctified: and for theſe cauſes our Saviour iterated their ordination to the paſtoral extraordinary and ordinary offices, and the rather leaſt his death might be thought to have made void their firſt more ſecret and covert ordination. Some late writers think, that Chriſt, leſt his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion into heaven might ſeem to have nullified the ſecond ordination, did ordain the Apoſtles the third time in the day of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> epiſt. ad Hedib. q. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> but its more likely that he did then onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete their ordination in the meaſure of extraordinary and ordinary gifts of the ſpirit, enabling them, and in them the ſucceeding Paſtors for the better execution of their paſtoral functions. Thirdly, the fathers agree alſo in this, that Chriſt gave equal power and authority unto all the Apoſtles and made them all miniſterial rocks and fundations,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi> de ſimplicit. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</note> gave unto
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93080:45"/>them the Keyes of the heavenly Kingdome, and gave them with the Keyes in their hands unto the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de verbis Domini ſerm. <hi>11.</hi> &amp; de doct. Chriſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> for whoſe ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification onely they and their ſucceſſors were to uſe them. The eyes are not more the bodies, then Paſtors and their Keyes are the Churches; and as the body cannot ſee but by the eyes, ſo the Church cannot enter into heaven by any other member (under Chriſt) of the myſtical body, without the ſervice of the Paſtors opening with their Keyes the gates of heaven for her. As the Apoſtles were miniſterial rocks, ſo was <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion an inſtrumental rock: and in a ſecond place, the confeſſion and preaching of the reſt of the Apoſtles were ſo too; by the means of which rocks the Church is built upon the foundation of foundations, the principal rock our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hilar. <hi>in</hi> Math. <hi>Can.</hi> 11. Matth. 16.</note> Yet <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion was not without a great reward: He had the firſt promiſe of the Keyes to be given unto him after Chriſt's reſurrection, with the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant meaſure of the grace of the Holy Ghoſt, which he then received with the reſt of the Apoſtles; yet ſo that he was the firſt in order which received them before the reſt. He had a name given him by our Saviour from the principal rock.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> ſerm. <hi>89. Cyprian.</hi> de habiiu virgin.</note> He was made the firſt in order and head of the Apoſtles: the firſt miniſterial rock: and his preaching was made the firſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental rock. He was made the firſt preacher to, and convertor of the Jews and Gentiles;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh. 10.</hi> &amp; <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> ſer. <hi>47.</hi> De <hi>Petro</hi> vide <hi>Aug.</hi> retract. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>21. Ambroſ.</hi> de incarn. Dom. ſacramento <hi>Cypr.</hi> nbi ſup. &amp; ad <hi>Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</hi>
               </note> the Apoſtle and Paſtor of the firſt Chriſtian Church after Chriſts aſcenſion, which was the mother of all other Churches. And becauſe it was believed that he had his choyceſt and longeſt reſidence in <hi>Rome,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by his miniſtery the Goſpel was firſt planted, that Church was counted the Princeſs of Churches, the mother of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as he was accounted and called the Prince of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. All theſe priviledges did ſerve to ſhew the unity of the Church, and the unity of the holy miniſtery and miniſters thereof, and to commend unto all the ſons of the Church, the preſervation of unity in doctrine, worſhip, Diſcipline and charity. There be many particular Churches of Chriſt, yet all but one Church, as <hi>Peters</hi> Church was one, there be many Biſhops and Presbyters, yet as <hi>Peter</hi> was alone the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the firſt Church which repreſented all the ſucceeding
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93080:46"/>Churches,<note place="margin">Baſil. conſtitut. Monaſt. c. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> ſo the many miniſters of the Goſpel are one in <hi>Peter,</hi> and the miniſtery one in him. And as the Churches and miniſters were one in their fountains and roots, ſo they ought to preſerve the like unity among themſelves, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters imitating the faithfulneſs of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the flock imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the obedience and holineſs of the Church of <hi>Peter.</hi> If <hi>Rome</hi> had perſiſted in, and contented her ſelf with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and not added thereto Idolatry, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and haereſies, we would gladly have owned and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Biſhops as the prime ſucceſſors of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the like ſucceſſor of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church: but, to our hearts unſpeakable grief we ſpeak it, the gold is become dimme, the moſt fine gold is changed, the holy City is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an harlot. O that ſhe would return to her firſt husband that we might return to her! Ther's <hi>Peter</hi>'s chair where <hi>Peter</hi>'s preaching is ſincerely imitated, that's <hi>Peters</hi> Church which imitates her faith and holineſs, which when <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall do, ſhe ſhall recover her precedency of ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Peter</hi> had a primacy among the Apoſtles, but no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority of command over them: All paſtors were in him firſt and ſecondarily in the reſt of the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">De dignitate Sacerd. c. <hi>2. Jo. 21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>) did not alone receive the ſheep, but received them with us, and we received them with him. Chriſt in the Apoſtles gave unto all Paſtors the power of ordaining Paſtors; becauſe he gave them the Keyes to be conveyed to ſucceſſors. But the power of appointing who among the Presbyters ſhould exerciſe them, and how, and who among them ſhould be governours of the uſe of the Keyes, was not conveyed with the Keyes to all Paſtors in the Apoſtolical ordination; becauſe it was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the extraordinary office of the Apoſtles, either to leave that to the wiſdome of the Church and ordinary Paſtors to order, or to ſettle it in one Presbyter aſſiſted with the Colledge of Presbyters, or otherwiſe, as the Holy Ghoſt ſhould guide them. We may not think that our Saviour did give unto every Presbyter power to ordain, preach, adminiſter the Sacraments, excommunicate, or abſolve, at his own will and pleaſure, without any appointment of a flock, or calling him to account of his Stewardſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for this is againſt the light of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93080:46"/>nature, unleſs God had given unto every Presbyter wiſdome and a will which could not erre in the orderly uſe of the Keyes, as he gave unto the Apoſtles; without which extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary grace the houſe of God in that caſe had been full of diſorder and confuſion, which Chriſt would not permit.</p>
            <p>If the power of diſpoſing and governing the act of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and the exerciſe of the acts of binding and looſing had been given to the body of the Presbyters by our Saviour, the Apoſtles and univerſal Church had never deprived the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that authority: Wherefore as the firſt planting of the Chriſtian Churches was proper to the Apoſtles, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting of the form of government, and the governors of the exerciſe of the acts of ordination, and the Keyes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted onely to their truſt. And it was very congruous that Chriſt would not determine the form of the government of his Church and Paſtors thereof before his aſcention into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the taking full poſſeſſion of his government and Kingdome at the right hand of his Father.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles planted the Churches after this manner: When God had bleſſed their miniſtery in Cities and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Towns, and in the Country adjacent, in the converſion of many to God, they conſtituted one congregation or Church of all the converts in that City or good Town and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try about it, So ordering Eccleſiaſtical Corporations as might, as much as could be, beſt agree with the civil corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and their diviſion. For the feeding of which Church they ordained Paſtors, and thoſe many in every City-Church,<note place="margin">Ubi eſt Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia niſi ubi vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga &amp; gratia floret ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> de <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> &amp; anima c. <hi>7.</hi> Es <hi>Hier.</hi> contra Lucifer. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia non eſt quoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non habet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem.</note> in which they left the Colledge of Presbyters governors both of the Paſtors individually conſidered, and the whole flock, yet with and under themſelves or their vicegerents as preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, when either of them were preſent. But within a ſhort time, when Chriſtianity was much ſpread in ſeveral Nations, and many City-Churches were grown populous, ſo that they had many leſſer Churches under them; and the Apoſtles and their Vicegerents could be preſent but in very few in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the far greater number which wanted their ſociety, the Colledges in theſe began to be divided among themſelves, and to divide the Churches, which cauſed the Apoſtles guided
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93080:47"/>thereto by the Spirit of Chriſt to conſent to a change of the government which was by the Colledges (bodies without a head, and ſo apt to ſwerve in ruling populous Churches) into a preſident in every Church choſen out of the Paſtors, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Colledge of the City and beſt Presbyters as his Senate and Counſellors. And then both the Apoſtles and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, or Apoſtolical helpers, which were extraordinary Biſhops, become ordinary Biſhops to be ſucceded by others. And theſe laſt were like our Arch-biſhops, having many Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops under them, as <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Creet, &amp;c.</hi> and the Apoſtles were like our Primates but of higher authority, and having more Arch-biſhops under them. Here we may obſerve, that the original occaſion of Epiſcopacy doth very much commend it, it being introduced to heal the evil of Schiſme, and, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting it for time to come, to ſecure the peace of the Church: And it hath and will be the more acceptable to the Churches, becauſe it was inſtituted or confirmed by the Apoſtles at their deſire.</p>
            <p>Unto the impoſition of hands, benediction and prayers (which were of the eſſence of the ordinations of Biſhops and Presbyters) many Ceremonies were in time added, ſome ſooner, ſome later, which ſerved to make a clearer mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Eccleſiaſtical powers received in and by them; which additional Ceremonies in time became occaſions of foul miſtakes: Some making the additions to be the eſſence of the ordinations, or part thereof; other multiplying the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apoſtles according to the diverſity of kinds of the powers, which they in very deed received, but in one or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, although iterated for ſome ſpecial reaſons.</p>
            <p>When the Schoolmen began to write, they found the Roman Court full of corrupt doctrine, which they thought themſelves bound to maintain, miſtaking &amp; miſcalling the evil good, and the good evil. They found in the ordination of a Presbyter the Patene with Bread, and the Cup with the Wine (both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſecrated) to be delivered unto the party to be ordained, with theſe words ſpoken by the Biſhop,<note place="margin">Cont. Florent. <hi>Sotus</hi> in <hi>4.</hi> d. <hi>24.</hi> &amp; <hi>Major</hi> &amp; <hi>Tho.</hi> in <hi>4.</hi> d. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Take power to offer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Ceremony added to that ordination about the year 700 (as is probable,) ſome Schoolmen, and alſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93080:47"/>Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, affirm to be the matter and forme of the conſecration of a Presbyter, making the impoſition of hands with the words, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> to belong onely to the ſolemnity thereof, and not to be eſſential to it; againſt the judgment of all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Other maintain the delivery of the Patene with Bread,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> in <hi>4.</hi> d. <hi>24. Vaſq.</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> diſp. <hi>239. Bellar.</hi> de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento ord. i. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and the Cup with wine in it, together with the ſaid words ſpoken by the Biſhop, to be one part of the ordination; and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands with the words, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</hi> to be an other part thereof; and both theſe parts to conſtitute the whole eſſence of the ordination: As if our Saviour had made the Apoſtles Presbyters by two diſtinct ordinations, the one before his death, and the other after his reſurrection, whereof the firſt (if we will without reaſon believe them) made them Prieſts, the ſecond gave them the power of bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and looſing, and made them complete Presbyters.</p>
            <p>As concerning the ordination of Biſhops, Divines (ſaith <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſq.</hi>) do not well agree at what time they were ordained,<note place="margin">In <hi>3.</hi> p. d. <hi>242.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Some think that Chriſt ordained them, when he ſaid, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt, Whoſe ſins ye remit, &amp;c.</hi> this opinion is juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by <hi>Vaſques;</hi> unleſs it may be made good, that Biſhops and Presbyters had one and the ſame ordination; for all grant that Presbyters were ordained by thoſe words. Other ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine <hi>Peter</hi> alone to have been imediately ordained by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and the reſt of the Apoſtles by <hi>Peter, &amp;c.</hi> ſo <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> and others: but this aſſertion doth not pleaſe <hi>Vaſques</hi> and we cannot be pleaſed with ſuch figments. Others doe conceive our Saviour to have ordained them Prieſts and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, when he ſaid, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me;</hi> This opinion is as falſe as the laſt. Some think them ordained in the day of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> and <hi>Vaſques</hi> himſelf thinks them to have been ordained, when Chriſt ſaid unto them, <hi>Go teach all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c.</hi> which is as groundleſs an opinion as any of the reſt: Whereas in truth when they were ordained Apoſtles, they were made Presbyters, having the paſtoral powers which were to be tranſmitted to ſucceſſors, and were alſo made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Biſhops, having as eſſential to their extraordinary
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93080:48"/>function of Apoſtleſhip, an extraordinary preſidency and ſuperintendency over the uſe and exerciſe of all the paſtoral offices, but were not made Biſhops, which were to be ſucceeded, until they themſelves, by confirming the prudent choice of the Churches, had inſtituted Epiſcopacy.</p>
            <p>The Schoolmen found the Laicks impower'd by commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from <hi>Rome, &amp;c.</hi> to excommunicate: Hence they diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the power of the Order and the power of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. We gather from the holy Scriptures and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitive Church, that excommunication was ordained to be a mean to bring a perſon, guilty of ſome ſcandalous ſin committed after Baptiſm, to the degree of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and humiliation; meet firſt, to receive pardon of ſin through faith in Chriſts blood. Secondly, to ſatisfie and edifie the Church by good example in proportion to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence given and harme done by his bad example. Thirdly, to take away the evil propenſity, the skars and blots made in the Soul by the ſin committed, and to reſtore the offender to the degree of purity of Soul, and conſequently of communion with God, and of Gods love to him which he enjoyed before his fall; which are obtained when God is glorified and pleaſed by the humiliation in proportion to the diſhonour done to God, and the divine diſpleaſure incurred by ſin. Fourthly, to receive more ſtrength to make the penitent able to ſtand, and avoid the like fall in time to come. In the firſt four Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies after our Saviours birth, a full abſolution was not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any Penitent (except in caſe of neceſſity) until the Biſhop and Presbyters judged his repentance and humiliation to have reſtored him to Gods grace and favour,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi> ad clerum. De Presbyteris qui temerè pacem lapſis dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Church, and to his former ſpiritual ſtrength in grace. And therefore we may be aſſured, that no man was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated from the Church militant, but in order to receive grace to reſtore him to and fit him for the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; and that it was the ſame Key which did ſhut the dores of both Churches againſt the offender, and was to open the dores unto him, having given ſufficient teſtimony of a due humiliation. The Catholick Church in the Primitive times did not divide excommunication into two diſtinct
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93080:48"/>kinds, that is, into excommunication from the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, and excommunication from the Church militant, the firſt proper to the Biſhop and Presbyter; and the other peculiar to the Biſhops and his Committees, Presbyters or lay; this to be exerciſed by the power of Juriſdiction the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to be exerciſed by the power of order, that is, the power which Biſhops and Presbyters received from Chriſt by their ordination. Whereby we underſtand the power of juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in this ſenſe as oppoſed to the power of order, to be the gift neither of Chriſt nor of his Apoſtles. If the Church gave this power, it was a corrupt Church that gave it, for by this ordinance of man the ordinance of Chriſt is made void; The ordinance of man, is exalted above the ordinance of Chriſt; for the excommunication which is Chriſts ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may be executed by the Presbyter (in ſubordination to the Biſhop, but) without his Commiſſion; the humane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication is made peculiar to the Biſhop the chief of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer in the Church, to be executed by himſelf or ſome other by his commiſſion. Much good do it to the Roman Biſhops whoſe cheif Biſhop firſt invented it: our Biſhops like it not, it hath been too importunate to ſtick (in part) unto them, but they will perfectly ſhake it off, as ſoon as they can.</p>
            <p>The excommunication which is Chriſts ordinance hath parts or members, whereby it may be more or leſs full, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer; but it ought not to be coupled with a mate, a brat of mans invention.<note place="margin">De paenitentia l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Munus Spiritu Sancti eſt offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, jus autem Spiritus Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti in ſolvend ligandis<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibuseſt. Ibi</note> 
               <hi>Deus par jus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>&amp; ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendi eſſe voluit &amp; ligandi:</hi> God would that there ſhould be equally, as a right of looſing, ſo a right of binding. And therefore he that hath not the right of looſing (ſaith he) neither hath he the right of binding. And a little after, he that hath (ſaith he) a right to looſe, he hath a right to bind. And a little after, the ſame Father ſaith, that this right (or power) of looſing and binding, is permitted onely to Prieſts (that is, Biſhops and Presbyters) and thence concludes that Hereticks which had no Prieſts could not challenge this power. Then this Holy man ſheweth the ſpring of the ſame power, he that receiveth the Holy Ghoſt (ſaith he) recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the power both of looſing and of binding, as it is written,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93080:49"/>
               <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jo. 20.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe ſius ye remit, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore he that cannot looſe ſin hath not the Holy Ghoſt (that is,<note place="margin">Si fictus eſt (Praesbyter aut Epiſcopus) Spiritus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Diſciplinae effugiet fictum, deeſt ſaluti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, miniſterium tamen ejus non deſerit, quo per eum ſalutem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratur alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Aug.</hi> contra e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>Parmen.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him an able miniſter of the New Teſtament, and of the ſpirit for the remiſſion of ſins.) Thus far <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Whereby we ſee that the Holy Ghoſt gives unto Biſhops and Presbyters the power of binding by excommunication, and of looſing by abſolution, and that the Holy Ghoſt doth accompany their ſervice to cure them that will not refuſe to be healed. Away then with the excommunication that hath not the Holy Spirit to warrant it, nor the operation of the Holy Ghoſt to make it effectual to mans ſalvation. Away with the lay ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication that makes the Holy Ghoſt a ſervant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it. Away with <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts made of the loweſt of the people, which are not of the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> which have not received the Holy Ghoſt to make them able miniſters of the new Teſtament, not of the letter but of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>It is the duty of the lay Chriſtian magiſtrate to overſee, facilitate and corroborate the due execution of the ſpiritual cenſure of excommunication performed by Biſhops princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally and Presbyters ſubordinately: but if any ask, whether he may not excommunicate either by himſelf or by a ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute? although the anſwer is already given in the premiſes, yet I ſay, he may do ſo, and if he have the gift, may preach in publick, and miniſter the holy Sacraments as lawfully as the 250 perſons ſpoken of in the ſixteenth chap. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> took cenſer and offered incenſe,<note place="margin">2 Chron. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> and as lawfully as King <hi>Uzziah</hi> did the like: And as to the curing of the Leproſy of the ſoul, he may expect the like ſucceſs as <hi>Naaman</hi> would have had as to the healing of the Leproſy of his body,<note place="margin">2 King. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> if he had waſhed himſelf in any other river then <hi>Jordan,</hi> wherein the Prophet commanded him to waſh himſelf in order to his cleanſing.</p>
            <p>The Kings Proclamation prevaileth more with many to leave their ſcandalous vices and to live ſoberly, then the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the beſt Biſhops and Presbyters uſually do with moſt men: Will any therefore conclude that the Proclamation of the King, is an effectual means for the infuſion of Gods ſaving grace, as well as the preaching of the Goſpel by them that are lawfully called to that ſacred work? the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93080:49"/>power is verſed about the externals of Chriſtian vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and reacheth onely accidentally and by Gods indulgence ſometime to the ſouls of men, and the life of virtues; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the miniſterial power of the Goſpel, is primarily ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be a means alwayes effectual for the infuſion of the ſoul and life of all ſaving Chriſtian virtues, if the operation of the Holy Ghoſt, which doth conſtantly work with the miniſtery of the Goſpel (in all the offices thereof,) be not deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſted. Men are ſaved by means inſtituted and ſanctified by the wiſdome and power of God, and not by means which onely the wiſdome of man judgeth to be moſt probable to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our eternal ſalvation. We live by faith, and not by ſenſe.</p>
            <p>The Independent congregations blame the reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops for ſome miſcarriages about the heavy cenſure of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and exclaim both againſt them, and againſt Presbyters for being more zealous for ceremonies, then for the due execution of our function in the maine offices thereof, and for the power of godlineſs. As for the abuſe of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, the blame was to have been imputed unto others, and not to the Biſhops. And to ſay the very truth, in this matter of excommunication, the Canons of our Church are defective and require amendment, which perhaps ſome invincible hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances would not permit to be done in times paſt. As for the miſplacing of the intention of our zeal; Firſt, as being my ſelf a Presbyter, although one of the meaneſt, I muſt anſwer for my ſelf, that although (it may be) no man will or can condemn me, yet truely I cannot juſtifie my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgment ſeat of Almighty God, but muſt make my earneſt ſupplication for mercy to my judge. I fear leaſt any ſoul miſcarry, or miſcarried through my default, that his blood ſhould be required at my hands; And therefore I tremble when I conſider what account I am to give of my Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And now having knowledge and experience of the moſt heavy weight of this ſacred vocation, and the great propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of our nature, ſtrengthened by manifold temptations, unto unfaithfulneſs therein, if I were now to enter into it, the conſcience of my weakneſs and fear of miſcarriage would cauſe me to decline it, but being long ſince entred, woe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93080:50"/>unto me if I preach not the Goſpel; and I will not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged having the power and mercy of God in whom I truſt to be my ſtrength and comfort. I deſire all good men, as charitably to cenſure us, ſo to pray earneſtly to God for us, that the great afflictions which we have ſuffered may be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to us, that remembring the afflictions and miſeries, the Wormwood and the Gall, our ſouls may be humbled in us, and that the extraordinary deliverance and bleſſings may entirely ingage our hearts to ſerve the Lord with all diligence and faithfulneſs in the holy miniſtery, and to feed the flock of God, taking the overſight thereof not by conſtraint but willingly, not for filthy Lucre (a peſtilence in the Church) but of a ready mind, neither being Lords over Gods Heritage (ſo unbecoming the meſſengers of the Lamb of God, who waſhed his Diſciples feet,) but being examples to the flock of ſobriety, humility, meekneſs, Chriſtian bounty to the poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it becomes not good men to cenſure us for uſing thoſe Rites and Ceremonies, which we are perſwaded not to be prohibited by Gods Law, and both they and we do ſurely know to be commanded to be uſed by mans Law duely made, which is Gods ordinance, to which we muſt be ſubject for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake. We pity the tender conſcience which cannot without offence either obey or diſobey that ordinance. And where any of a good life is ſeen to have that tenderneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the malignity of pride, and labour to propagate it and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church, the piety and diſcretion of the Biſhop will uſe him gently, inſtruct him, pray for him, waite patiently for his amendment, and, unleſſe the example of the party is ſeen to corrupt the ſound, will hardly be drawn to go beyond a threatning, becauſe puniſhment to a man of that temper, ſeems rather to be an addition of miſery to him, then whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Phyſick meet to cure him.</p>
            <p>If any will attempt to be Authors of Combinations, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, by ſhew of multitudes and by tumults, the alteration or abrogation of any part of the eſtabliſhed laws Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, they will thereby evidently manifeſt themſelves to be but meer pretenders to a tender conſcience and power of godlineſs; for they that labour to extort a part, if they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93080:50"/>prevaile, muſt have the whole in their power. And can they that attempt ſo great robbery love God, and the power of Godlineſs? By this curſed fruit we know theſe to be moſt vile Hypocrites. Let no good people be deceived by their ſheeps cloathing; look upon this bitter fruit, and you ſee that they are within but greedy and ravening Wolves:<note place="margin">Contra epiſt. Parmen. l. <hi>2.13.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> apud The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. balſam. c. <hi>5.</hi> Vide Baron an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. an. <hi>389.</hi> ſect. <hi>74.</hi> &amp; conc. African. temp. Bonifac. &amp; caeleſtin. c. <hi>15.</hi> Conc. earth. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Greg. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> God deliver us from them, and deliver them from the wickedneſs of their hearts and wayes: but leaving theſe I proceed. It is very pertinent to the matter in hand to ſpeak of reordination; but becauſe this ſubject is two large, I will onely ſay thus much, that St. <hi>Aug.</hi> and the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all antiquity are againſt reordination, as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt rebaptization, both truely ſo called. In caſes of doubt whether one were truely baptiſed or truely ordained, it was never accounted a rebaptization to baptiſe the one, or reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to ordain the other. The ordination of a Presbyter by Presbyters without Commiſſion from a Biſhop; was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes judged of dubious validity at the leaſt. Some ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in foreine Churches were not rejected by the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I believe, becauſe they thought that to judge of the fact of another Church in matter of no greater moment would not tend to ſtrengthen unity between the Churches, but rather to diminiſh and weaken it; Or, it may be, they did not admit them, as certainly knowing them to be ſo ordained, but as charitably believing they had been ordained by a Biſhop, for charity covereth the multitude of ſins: a doubtful ordination eſtabliſhed in all the parts of it, by the publick conſent and authority of a Church is far more tolerable, then the like ordination celebrated in all the parts of it, without and againſt the legal conſent and authority of the Church. For in this laſt caſe, many are doubtful of the validity of Baptiſm, and the other divine ordinances admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by them that were ſo ordained. But the Higher power partly hath, and in convenient time will remove all ſuch doubts to the full ſatisfaction of all good men. I have already exceeded my intended brevity. I will ſay no more, but deſire the candid reader to believe that I have not maintained E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy to be an inſtitution of Chriſt by the Apoſtles, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93080:51"/>not an inſtitution of Chriſt in the Apoſtles (as ſome hold, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by many fair probabilities) out of a ſpirit of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; but becauſe the ſentence choſen by me ſeems to be ſubject to leſs difficulties, and more agreeable to the ancient paſtoral and Epiſcopal ordinations which be received and uſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and eſpecially becauſe it doth more incline and conduce to moderation. Whatſoever I have herein written, I humbly ſubmit to the judgement and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of my Superiors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim Epiſcopi propter nos ſumus, ſed propter eos quibus ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum &amp; Sacramentum Dominicum miniſtramus; ac per hoc ut eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſine ſcandalo gubernandorum ſeſe neceſſitas tulerit, ita vel eſſe vel non eſſe debemus, quod non propter nos ſed propter alios ſumus.</hi> Aug <hi>contra</hi> Creſcon. <hi>Grammatic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:93080:51"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. line penult. after [of the Apoſtles] add [before our Saviours death] <hi>p.</hi> 10. marg. <hi>r.</hi> Jubain. <hi>p.</hi> 14. marg. <hi>r.</hi> in Eſai. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> dicit. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>r.</hi> dicit. ib. <hi>r.</hi> conſecratione. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>r.</hi> poſtea. <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 10. dele [of] exped. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> penult. <hi>r.</hi> ſaith. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>r.</hi> enable [them] the. <hi>p</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r.</hi> whom. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>r. Walafridus. p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 31. <hi>r.</hi> Tungrenſ. ſo in marg. pro Vigrenſ. <hi>r.</hi> Tungrenſ. <hi>p,</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>r.</hi> within ten. in marg. <hi>r.</hi> natalem Domini Toletan. the quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ubi multorum is miſplaced. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>r.</hi> Paſchal VVax. candle. <hi>p.</hi> 46. over againſt <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> in marg. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen.</hi> contra <hi>Hunom.</hi> Orat. 16. <hi>p.</hi> 47. ult. <hi>r.</hi> Catechumens. <hi>p.</hi> 51. in marg. dele [<hi>Paulinus</hi> in vita <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>] <hi>l.</hi> 10. marg. <hi>r.</hi> c. 5. <hi>p.</hi> 53. in marg. dele [per] <hi>Socrat. p.</hi> 54. in marg. pro praecip. <hi>r.</hi> princip. <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> Chorepiſcope. <hi>p.</hi> 59. for Miniſter, all, <hi>r.</hi> Miniſteriall. <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> 70 diſcip. in marg. <hi>r.</hi> Dracontium. Aug. in Pſal. 44. <hi>l.</hi> ult. dele (and.) <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> Brethren [.] — of [the] <hi>l.</hi> 13. dele [whoſe Succeſsors] <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>r.</hi> ſucceede. <hi>p.</hi> 69. marg. <hi>r.</hi> paenit: after <hi>r.</hi> [profecti] in pagum.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may be, that, by reaſon of the Authours abſence and ſome obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Copy, a few other faults may have eſcaped undiſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as miſplacing ſome Authors cited in the Margent, or in the Figures, or in Pointing, and the like, which being ſmall, the goodneſs of the Reader will eaſily pardon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
